<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Philosophocle</title>
    <link href="http://holdenlee.github.io/philosophocle/atom.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="http://holdenlee.github.io/philosophocle" />
    <id>http://holdenlee.github.io/philosophocle/atom.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Scholars of Philosophocle</name>
        <email></email>
    </author>
    <updated>2016-02-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>Not a special day</title>
    <link href="http://holdenlee.github.io/philosophocle/posts/leap-day.html" />
    <id>http://holdenlee.github.io/philosophocle/posts/leap-day.html</id>
    <published>2016-02-29T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[
<div class="container">
  <div id="content">
    <div class="page header">
      <h1>Not a special day</h1>
    </div>
    <div class="info">
      
       
        <p class="subs">by Professor Whyse
	</p>
      
       
        <p class="subs">on 2016-02-29
	</p>
      
    </div>
    
  </div>
  <!--/div-->

  <hr>

  

  <div class="blog-main">
    <p>Fron has informed me that that today is a special day in the outside world called “leap day.” <!--more--> In every country besides ours, February has 28 days, except when it has 29 days, which happens every 4th year except every 100th year except every 400th year.</p>
<p>“<em>29 days?</em>” Un asks, surprised and indignant, when I pass on the information to him. “Even when February earns an extra day, she still has fewer days than any other month?”</p>
<p>Un finds such a custom symptomatic of the capitalistic and despotic tendencies of the outside world. A philosophy of inequality permeates their society so deeply that it manifests itself in their basic conception of time.</p>
<p>“Like February, the poor stay poor,” Un says, “Once in a while they are given money or opportunity. And then? ‘Just kidding!’ as the Americans would say. Back to another 3 years of being <em>even shorter</em> than everyone else!”</p>
<p>I of course challenge Un to demonstrate a link between foreign calendars and capitalism. After some well-spent hours on hemerological research, Un explains to me that the rulers of old, such as Augustus Caesar, had the habit of naming months after themselves, and stealing days from other months until their own namesake had 31 days. (They are quite foolish to believe that mortal humans can alter the flow of time in any way, for calendars are only artificial constructs. Time is a continuum, infinitely divisible and infinitely long, as beautiful, God-given, and untouchable by humans as the real numbers.<a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"><sup>1</sup></a>) February, formerly the last month of the year, was the natural target of temporal theft.</p>
<p>But, foreign reader, you must be wondering about our own calendary practices! In our calendary, all months have either 30 or 31 days, as is reasonable. This year, February has 30 days, as does its brother March. The intercalary (leap) day is shared among months as in a cooperative society; this year, May has the good fortune of having 31 days.</p>
<p>Visitors often gripe about our system, staring dumbfoundedly at the discrepancy between the complimentary “Seasons of Philosophocle” calendars we offer them and their cell-phone clocks. Their frowns betray their thoughts: How dare a backwards society like ours inconvenience them with a date change! I beg to differ. It is us who are leading the way in egalitarianism, and the rest of the world refuses to follow.</p>
<p>Some of our banks have caved to the pressure of the outside world. It seems that the date discrepancy has caused many glitches, including the loss of thousands of dollars, and investors going berserk on the phone while the bank tellers try unsuccessfully to give them a practical course in anger management. Here at Philosophocle, however, we are thankfully under no such financial pressure, and are free to pursue the higher fruits of intellectual endeavors.</p>
<section class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Dave informs me that many physicists disagree. In particular, it may be possible for humans to be immortal by falling into “black holes”. This, however, does not sound like a pleasant experience.<a href="#fnref1">↩</a></p></li>
</ol>
</section>

  </div>

    

    <!-- Previous/next post-->
    <div>
    
    
    </div>
    <br>

    <!-- Extension : Sharing buttons @ www.sharethis.com -->
    <span class='st_facebook_large' displayText='Facebook'></span>
    <span class='st_twitter_large' displayText='Tweet'></span>
    <span class='st_googleplus_large' displayText='Google +'></span>
    <span class='st_reddit_large' displayText='Reddit'></span>
    <span class='st__large' displayText=''></span>

    <div id="disqus_thread"></div>
    


  
    <script>!function(d,s,id){var js,fjs=d.getElementsByTagName(s)[0],p=/^http:/.test(d.location)?'http':'https';if(!d.getElementById(id)){js=d.createElement(s);js.id=id;js.src=p+'://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js';fjs.parentNode.insertBefore(js,fjs);}}(document, 'script', 'twitter-wjs');</script>
  </div>
  
</div>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Bloodfields</title>
    <link href="http://holdenlee.github.io/philosophocle/posts/bloodfields.html" />
    <id>http://holdenlee.github.io/philosophocle/posts/bloodfields.html</id>
    <published>2016-02-26T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[
<div class="container">
  <div id="content">
    <div class="page header">
      <h1>Bloodfields</h1>
    </div>
    <div class="info">
      
       
        <p class="subs">by Professor Whyse
	</p>
      
       
        <p class="subs">on 2016-02-26
	</p>
      
    </div>
    
  </div>
  <!--/div-->

  <hr>

  

  <div class="blog-main">
    <p>Dave, the techie, has created glasses that filter out non-red light. Thus, looking at the snowfields outside, we see fields of red that make us want to vomit. <!--more--> This reminds us that although snow insinuates itself as a symbol of purity and innocence, it is the cause of widespread death: many a family has met tragedy when their breadwinner dies in a snow-related traffic accident on eir way to work.</p>
<p>These “blood-glasses” help us keep our focus, especially when we are feeling discouraged in our academic work: not only will we resist the hypnotic tendency to stare at the mounds of freshly-fallen snow and let our minds go blank, we will turn up our lips in disgust at the masochistic students building bloodmen (who will bleed to death slowly when the sun shines) outside, and aggressively close the window shades to avoid nausea, instead seeking refuge in our books.</p>
<p>When I suggested to Dave that his invention would have been much more useful back in December, he told me that he, too, had been willfully blind to the dangers of snow until his father’s death. Despite the fact that the snow will soon melt, however, all his glasses have sold out, as many students reasoned that they would be cheaper now than at the beginning of next winter, just as The Shop of Forgotten Things marks up the prices of its umbrellas by 10% during rainy days. Dave reports that some of these students have found a secondary use of the glasses for the non-winter months ahead of us.</p>
<p>“Blue light at night is harmful to our circadian rhythms,” Klarissa says, citing a research article on human biology, “so we use the glasses to study late while minimizing the effects on our sleep.”</p>
<p>Dave apologizes for the shortage, and promises that before next winter, he will have manufactured many more such glasses.</p>

  </div>

    

    <!-- Previous/next post-->
    <div>
    
    
    </div>
    <br>

    <!-- Extension : Sharing buttons @ www.sharethis.com -->
    <span class='st_facebook_large' displayText='Facebook'></span>
    <span class='st_twitter_large' displayText='Tweet'></span>
    <span class='st_googleplus_large' displayText='Google +'></span>
    <span class='st_reddit_large' displayText='Reddit'></span>
    <span class='st__large' displayText=''></span>

    <div id="disqus_thread"></div>
    


  
    <script>!function(d,s,id){var js,fjs=d.getElementsByTagName(s)[0],p=/^http:/.test(d.location)?'http':'https';if(!d.getElementById(id)){js=d.createElement(s);js.id=id;js.src=p+'://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js';fjs.parentNode.insertBefore(js,fjs);}}(document, 'script', 'twitter-wjs');</script>
  </div>
  
</div>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Clarifications</title>
    <link href="http://holdenlee.github.io/philosophocle/posts/clarifications.html" />
    <id>http://holdenlee.github.io/philosophocle/posts/clarifications.html</id>
    <published>2016-02-24T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[
<div class="container">
  <div id="content">
    <div class="page header">
      <h1>Clarifications</h1>
    </div>
    <div class="info">
      
       
        <p class="subs">by Professor Whyse
	</p>
      
       
        <p class="subs">on 2016-02-24
	</p>
      
    </div>
    
  </div>
  <!--/div-->

  <hr>

  

  <div class="blog-main">
    <p>After my student, Fron, ran to my office excitedly yesterday evening, saying the weblog was up, I eagerly followed him to the computer lab. <!--more--> Many of our students were gathered around the screen. They watched me connect to the “Internet”, open the “browser”, and type in the “address” of our weblog.<a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"><sup>1</sup></a></p>
<p>I was dismayed. Where was the introduction that I had mailed to our webmaster two weeks ago? Only after I had mailed the introduction did Fron inform me that it would be faster to send it over the Internet. This is what I did for the <a href="the-street.html">second post</a>. I typed it up and gave it to Fron, who told me with a frustrated look on his face that I was not supposed to type it with a typewriter, but a computer, or it would not get turned into bits to be sent over the Internet!</p>
<p>I had closed my eyes and told Fron, “Breathe. Is it right for you to be frustrated at your professor? Given how many times professors have patiently explained things to you while possibly harboring unspoken thoughts about your lack of intelligence, could you not return the favor?”</p>
<p>Fortunately, Fron is not Lisa, and was immediately chastised. He then proceeded to re-type the post and e-mail it. I believe Fron is a good student, even though he often gets caught in the spur of the moment. There is a reason that students in his year are called “sophomores.”</p>
<p>After some discussion, we realized why my second post was up but not the first. I had communicated to the webmaster that my post was not to be published until he had received the other post as well. Fron, however, being more versed in electronic mail, had e-mailed a post of his own, before my handwritten post had arrived, triggering the webmaster’s criterion to publish prematurely. Together we decided to email the webmaster to clear up the confusion, and apologize for the lack of an introductory post.</p>
<p>Our next topic of discussion was Fron’s post. “Of all the topics you could have weblogged about, why did you choose <a href="PHSS.html">PHSS</a>? And of all the wonderful shows we have on PHSS, why did you choose the unnamed radio hour? I find this narrowly focused article unrepresentative of our institution.”</p>
<p>“But professor, Dr. Drim told us in Creative Writing class that it is always better to be specific than general, and that we should write about what moves us emotionally, rather than what we feel like is ‘representative’. There is no one article that can be representative of Philosophocle, because Philosophocle is made of disparate parts. (Perhaps we should change our motto to ‘pinnacles of higher education’?) How can we have true cultural exchange if we only exchange the parts that are ‘representative’?”</p>
<p>I admitted that Fron had a point, and turned to the more pressing issue of the missing post. I suggested that the webmaster backdate the introductory post to be the first post. However, the webmaster informed me in the e-mail chat that he had not yet received the introductory post!</p>
<p>“Professor,” Fron said over my shoulder, “Backdating is something that the outside world does, usually for financial gain. We do not want to associate ourselves with that, do we?”</p>
<p>Once again I had to admit my student was right. It is uncertain when the introductory post will arrive. The webmaster has assured me he will put it up immediately after he receives it.</p>
<p>I feel like I am behind the times. After some bargaining, Fron has agreed to teach me the basics of computers<a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"><sup>2</sup></a>, in return for some tutoring in philosophy. I naturally agreed.</p>
<section class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>The use of such a familiar term around unfamiliar technology is comforting. I find the term “browser”, however, a misnomer, for it reminds me of the actions of zebras on the safari. Fron informed me that it is that other meaning of “browse” that is intended, namely, looking cursorily and non-seriously through documents. I object to this meaning because of its connotation: will foreign eyes look cursorily and non-seriously at the going-ons in our institution?<a href="#fnref1">↩</a></p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>I told him that I had read a book on Computability Theory. However, he informed me that this was not relevant to actual computers.<a href="#fnref2">↩</a></p></li>
</ol>
</section>

  </div>

    

    <!-- Previous/next post-->
    <div>
    
    
    </div>
    <br>

    <!-- Extension : Sharing buttons @ www.sharethis.com -->
    <span class='st_facebook_large' displayText='Facebook'></span>
    <span class='st_twitter_large' displayText='Tweet'></span>
    <span class='st_googleplus_large' displayText='Google +'></span>
    <span class='st_reddit_large' displayText='Reddit'></span>
    <span class='st__large' displayText=''></span>

    <div id="disqus_thread"></div>
    


  
    <script>!function(d,s,id){var js,fjs=d.getElementsByTagName(s)[0],p=/^http:/.test(d.location)?'http':'https';if(!d.getElementById(id)){js=d.createElement(s);js.id=id;js.src=p+'://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js';fjs.parentNode.insertBefore(js,fjs);}}(document, 'script', 'twitter-wjs');</script>
  </div>
  
</div>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>PHSS</title>
    <link href="http://holdenlee.github.io/philosophocle/posts/PHSS.html" />
    <id>http://holdenlee.github.io/philosophocle/posts/PHSS.html</id>
    <published>2016-02-23T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[
<div class="container">
  <div id="content">
    <div class="page header">
      <h1>PHSS</h1>
    </div>
    <div class="info">
      
       
        <p class="subs">by Fron
	</p>
      
       
        <p class="subs">on 2016-02-23
	</p>
      
    </div>
    
  </div>
  <!--/div-->

  <hr>

  

  <div class="blog-main">
    <p>Studying late at night, it can be tempting to turn on the radio to see what is playing on the school’s station, PHSS (pronounced, “fiss”). At 3 or 4 in the morning, the programs are often unconventional. <!--more--> One day it might be “Mocha moves dance music,” another day it might be one student’s sleepless soliloquy on the current state of the world, another day it might be “the sound of various things dropping, like pins, toilet paper rolls, and feathers,” on another, it might be a student reciting a book of “American Knock-knock jokes.” It is fascinating, during those early-morning nights when one feels that one is the only person alive in the world, to feel oneself on the periphery as one tunes in to the story of another’s life - or as much of it as can be inferred from the crackly soundwaves.</p>
<p>I discovered these programs when, one night, grabbing my alarm-clock-cum-radio from my bedside table to check my remaining time to sleep before my early flight, accidentally hit the “on” switch. I soon forgot all about sleep as I listened to a mellifluous voice talking about various luminescent creatures in the deep sea. Those soundwaves have echoed in my head as I traveled from Philosophocle, and became a symbol for nostalgia: for in my travels abroad, I have never heard a voice so content with esoterica as the mysterious stranger on that radio whom I have never been able to identify.</p>
<p>Since then I have been a follower of this unnamed radio hour, “programming” my radio to turn on for one hour and whisper into my pillow. Many times, some of the words warp into my dreams. Today, however, I was jolted awake by a voice unlike any I had heard previously, “You know what, no one is listening at this time of night anyway, so I can do whatever I want! I think I’m going to play this favorite tune of mine, it’s called armpit farting, by Yours Truly!” I need not describe the cacophony that followed; I had to shut off the radio and whisper “luminescent jellyfish” a few hundred times before I could fall asleep again.</p>
<p>When I woke up, I prepared to let the radio program be a forgotten nightmare. Imagine my horror when, arriving at Introduction to Data Science just in time as the teacher started lecture (using the methods of the course, over a period of 20 days I had found the exact second I should leave the dorm to arrive on time to class 95% of the time), I found that the entire front row of students had started to engage in that vulgar activity, and the rest of the class was erupting in laughs, some genuine and some uneasy! I had always thought myself one of few that listened to the unnamed radio hour, but now I realize my error in believing that something so interesting could escape the attention of students who fed on soul-enlightening moments. (It is the same error of romanticizing that one is the only person in existence late at night.) The whole incident had become “viral,” and a quite many people had obtained recordings of the 11:58 performance, much to my dismay in the rest of the classes. I wished I could be as nonchalant as the professors, who knew that to object was the fan the flames of student ridicule (“throwing nuts from heaven”), but could only, alas, whisper “luminescent jellyfish” to myself.</p>
<p>No one was happier about the incident than Yano, whose thesis had been “Virality as a natural phenomenon.” We had prided ourselves on the resistance of Philosophocle to the crass forms of virality that, in the outside, digitized world, was symptomatic of attention deficit disorder, temptation irresistance, and a general sense of modern meaninglessness, so Yano had little to write about until today, when he can be found dashing from classroom to dining area to common room with a recorder on hand, cataloguing the first viral outbreak as it occurred.</p>

  </div>

    

    <!-- Previous/next post-->
    <div>
    
    
    </div>
    <br>

    <!-- Extension : Sharing buttons @ www.sharethis.com -->
    <span class='st_facebook_large' displayText='Facebook'></span>
    <span class='st_twitter_large' displayText='Tweet'></span>
    <span class='st_googleplus_large' displayText='Google +'></span>
    <span class='st_reddit_large' displayText='Reddit'></span>
    <span class='st__large' displayText=''></span>

    <div id="disqus_thread"></div>
    


  
    <script>!function(d,s,id){var js,fjs=d.getElementsByTagName(s)[0],p=/^http:/.test(d.location)?'http':'https';if(!d.getElementById(id)){js=d.createElement(s);js.id=id;js.src=p+'://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js';fjs.parentNode.insertBefore(js,fjs);}}(document, 'script', 'twitter-wjs');</script>
  </div>
  
</div>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>The Street</title>
    <link href="http://holdenlee.github.io/philosophocle/posts/the-street.html" />
    <id>http://holdenlee.github.io/philosophocle/posts/the-street.html</id>
    <published>2016-02-22T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[
<div class="container">
  <div id="content">
    <div class="page header">
      <h1>The Street</h1>
    </div>
    <div class="info">
      
       
        <p class="subs">by Professor Whyse
	</p>
      
       
        <p class="subs">on 2016-02-22
	</p>
      
    </div>
    
  </div>
  <!--/div-->

  <hr>

  

  <div class="blog-main">
    <p>In Philosophocle, the street is lined with cafes and snackeries. Each advertises a different atmosphere. The high-class Starset has individual tables, uniformed waiters with silver-star badges, mochas drawn in the shape of maidens, and hot chocolate in tall glasses with swirly chocolate straws. The crowd-pleasing Delites offers bubble tea, self-serve yogurt machines with toppings, and mochis in tantalizing rows beneath cartoon pictures of themselves, the color of their filling leaking through their faces like a soft blush. <!--more--> Simplitea provides a tea bag, hot water, and a place to sit for 50 cents. At Delites you go with a group of friends - no one will pay attention to you if you go alone - but at Serendipiteas, you are ushered in to a random seat, facing someone you do not know. In Melli’s Flows the conversations never stop, hurried on by the always-present bubbling fountain (careful: the fish bite), and guests are encouraged to journey from table to table, with different h’ors d’oveures at each table to tempt (free with entrance ticket).</p>
<p>There are tea houses to suit every taste - for the poor and the rich, for those who enjoy talking about the weather<a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"><sup>1</sup></a> to those who enjoy talking about ancient philosophy, world problems, or the most vulnerable yearning parts of one’s soul. (There is one for quick romances as well, Impassioatta.) I would suggest consulting the Unofficial Guide to Tea, released by the Students for Students Club at the University, but it is not updated as often as the teahouses change managers or compete to put up new menus, so it is easy to fall out of date. On the plus side, there has been a recent influx of art majors on the Committee, and they have decided to represent the major flavors of tea and coffee at the different teahouses with characters, which they give personalities - Green at The Leafy Bough is a gentleman in a suit, who will proffer you napkins before you ask for them, as opposed to Silk at Melli’s, a smooth-talking man in a rainbow shirt whose hands are always moving, as opposed to Matcha at Delites, a plump little girl who will tell you all about the newest episodes of the current anime that is sweeping those into Eastern culture.</p>
<p>Recently there has been a new addition. The Electric Eel, it is called, and it looks like it has been dropped here from another continent. It has an imported neon sign that flashes, its mascot eel alternating between blue and electric yellow. It is taking a lot of business away from the other teahouses. They dim their lights, turn on fog machines during the evenings, and serve iced tea rather than hot tea. If you ask me, they dilute the tea with too many ice cubes, but a lot of people seem to like clinking them around in their glasses. There is a dance floor, with strips of light flowing around the walls. There is some guy there who gives dance lessons, not the kind of ballroom dancing you do with a partner, but a dance you do individually. I hear that it is amazing, people lined up in rows trying to copy the Great Danzini as they creak their joints in 360 degrees of movement and the “disco ball” alternately spotlights different amateur dancers. No one knows whether there is one Danzini or three or ten, behind his mask - how can one man stay up dancing every night for so many hours? He never talks. He gets lots of tips.</p>
<p>I am not so sure about the Electric Eel. Some of us think it is a bad influence from the Continent, where such things are called “nightclubs” and are home to uncontrolled lewdness (Impassionatta, on the other hand, is quite controlled.). But we of course let the students have their fun, as long as they are not violent.</p>
<section class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Talking about the weather at Philosophocle is a very serious matter! For it is impossible to reduce the state of the weather to a word like “cloudy” or “sunny,” the emotions of the sky are more variegated than the emotions of people, being so much vaster in scope.<a href="#fnref1">↩</a></p></li>
</ol>
</section>

  </div>

    

    <!-- Previous/next post-->
    <div>
    
    
    </div>
    <br>

    <!-- Extension : Sharing buttons @ www.sharethis.com -->
    <span class='st_facebook_large' displayText='Facebook'></span>
    <span class='st_twitter_large' displayText='Tweet'></span>
    <span class='st_googleplus_large' displayText='Google +'></span>
    <span class='st_reddit_large' displayText='Reddit'></span>
    <span class='st__large' displayText=''></span>

    <div id="disqus_thread"></div>
    


  
    <script>!function(d,s,id){var js,fjs=d.getElementsByTagName(s)[0],p=/^http:/.test(d.location)?'http':'https';if(!d.getElementById(id)){js=d.createElement(s);js.id=id;js.src=p+'://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js';fjs.parentNode.insertBefore(js,fjs);}}(document, 'script', 'twitter-wjs');</script>
  </div>
  
</div>
]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
