<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Mental Wilderness</title>
    <link href="http://holdenlee.github.io/blog/atom.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="http://holdenlee.github.io/blog" />
    <id>http://holdenlee.github.io/blog/atom.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Holden Lee</name>
        <email>oldheneel@gmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <updated>2021-02-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>2012-2 Short stories</title>
    <link href="http://holdenlee.github.io/blog/posts/reading/2021-2-short-stories.html" />
    <id>http://holdenlee.github.io/blog/posts/reading/2021-2-short-stories.html</id>
    <published>2021-02-21T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-02-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[
<div class="container">
  <div id="content">
    <div class="page header">
      <h1>2012-2 Short stories</h1>
    </div>
    
    <div class="info">
       <div class="subtitle"><p>Recommendations</p></div> 
       
        <p>Posted: 2021-02-21 
          , Modified: 2021-02-21 
	</p>
      
       <p>Tags: <a href="/tags/fiction.html">fiction</a>, <a href="/tags/short%20story.html">short story</a>, <a href="/tags/speculative%20fiction.html">speculative fiction</a></p> 
    </div>
    
  </div>
  <!--/div-->

  

  <div class="blog-main">
    <h2 id="two-short-stories-a-day">Two short stories a day…</h2>
<p>Since November, I’ve been reading an average of 2 short stories every day, mostly science fiction and fantasy.</p>
<p>As Junot Diaz once told me, “Read a thousand short stories and you’ll know how to write one.” It’s been good to immerse myself in story every day and get a idea of the variety of things out there. I’m cataloguing all the short stories I read in a table (using <a href="https://airtable.com/">airtable</a>), where I jot down basic information about the story, quotes I like, and rate it so I can easily find it later. As of today, it has 367 entries (of which 58 have 5-star ratings).</p>
<p>Every few months, I plan to go back through my list and post the stories I liked the most. They may or may not actually have been published recently.</p>
<p>I welcome recommendations for stories! Just leave a comment.</p>
<h2 id="top-picks">Top picks</h2>
<p>Here are the short stories I enjoyed the most the past few months.</p>
<p><strong><a href="http://www.beneath-ceaseless-skies.com/">Beneath Ceaseless Skies</a></strong></p>
<p>Literary adventure fantasy</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.beneath-ceaseless-skies.com/stories/when-your-being-here-is-gentler-than-your-absence-hard/">When Your Being Here is Gentler Than Your Absence Hard, Filip Hajdar Drnovšek Zorko</a> (Beneath Ceaseless Skies #322, 2021/1/28 #323, 2021/2/11) Fantasy, time travel, romance, excellent characterization, leading a nation in war, second person.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.beneath-ceaseless-skies.com/stories/her-black-coal-heart-a-diamond-in-my-hand/">Her Black Coal Heart a Diamond in My Hand, R.K. Duncan</a> (Beneath Ceaseless Skies #322, 2021/1/28) An artist gathers ghosts to create haunted houses to elicit donations for poverty.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.beneath-ceaseless-skies.com/stories/a-feast-from-tile-and-stone/">A Feast from Tile and Stone, Ryan Eric Dull</a> (Beneath Ceaseless Skies, #317) A team of chefs making an extravagant feast and dealing with a murder. (Think Scott Lynch, Sinspire-type extravagance.)</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><a href="https://www.sfsite.com/fsf/">Fantasy &amp; Science Fiction</a></strong></p>
<p>(Subscription required)</p>
<ul>
<li>The Dark Ride, John Kessel. Two realities/political assassinations intertwined, one on Earth and one on the moon. Political commentary, capitalism vs. socialism/anarchy. A tribute to old-time SF (e.g. Princess of Mars).</li>
<li>Interludes with the Gunwright, Jonathan L. Howard (Fantasy &amp; Science Fiction, 2021/1.) A gunwright and a soldier, over the years. Two strong female characters. I’m usually not a fan of guns, but the delightful writing won me over.</li>
<li>The Fairy Egg, R.S. Benedict (Fantasy &amp; Science Fiction, 2020/9.) A woman trying to escape the lower-class by selling “fairy eggs” and dealing with her husband’s toxic masculinity. Great characterization/commentary of the modern upper class.</li>
<li>Of Them All, Leah Cypress. (Fantasy &amp; Science Fiction, 2020/9) A fairy’s gift/curse: to be seen as beautiful only by those who hate you.</li>
<li>A Civilized and Orderly Zombie Apocalypse Per School Regulations, Sarina Dorie. The best pandemic-inspired story I have seen. Great teacher perspective.</li>
<li>On Vapor, Which the Night Condenses, Gregor Hartmann. (Fantasy &amp; Science Fiction, 2020/11.) A murder mystery at a edgy smell-based art exhibition.</li>
<li>How to Burn Down the Hinterlands, Lyndsie Manusos. (Fantasy &amp; Science Fiction, November 2020) An orphan blacksmith struggling against the empire that killed her mother and tries to enslave her. Swords forged from anger.</li>
<li>The Bahrain Underground Bazaar, Nadia Afifi. (Fantasy &amp; Science Fiction, November 2020) A grandpa with a lot of agency. Neural recordings. Turning back from suicide.</li>
<li>Eyes of the Forest, Ray Nayler (Fantasy &amp; Science Fiction, May 2020.) Learning to survive on an alien planet.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><a href="http://clarkesworldmagazine.com/">Clarkesworld</a></strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://clarkesworldmagazine.com/xiu_10_20/">All Living Creation, Xiu Xinyu</a> (Clarkesworld #169, 2020/10. Science Fiction World, 2017/6). Corporations enslaving clones of your sister.</li>
<li><a href="http://clarkesworldmagazine.com/chi_12_20/">No Way Back, Chi Hui</a> (Clarkesworld, 2020/12. Science Fiction World, 2006/5.) Escaping into cyberspace and losing your body.</li>
<li><a href="http://clarkesworldmagazine.com/wise_11_20/">To Sail the Black, A.C. Wise</a> (Clarkesworld, 2020/11.) A space pirate captain trying to save her ship, grappling with her decisions. A dying star.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><a href="https://dreamforgemagazine.com/">Dreamforge</a></strong></p>
<p>Optimistic, uplifting stories. I read a bunch of back issues because that’s what I’m in the mood for these days. (Subscription required)</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://dreamforge.mywebportal.app/dreamforge/stories/show/the-winds-and-waters-of-mars-c-h-hung">The Winds and Waters of Mars, C.H. Hung</a> (Dreamforge #7.) An American-born Chinese dealing with prejudice against immigrants, on Earth and on Mars.</li>
<li><a href="https://dreamforge.mywebportal.app/dreamforge/stories/show/myself-rebecca-enzor">Myself, Rebecca Enzor</a> (Dreamforge #7.) A short and inspiring story about a wish-granter learning to wish for freedom.</li>
<li><a href="https://dreamforge.mywebportal.app/dreamforge/stories/show/broke-down-and-starside-jennifer-shelby">Broke Down &amp; Starside, Jennifer Shelby</a> (Dreamforge #7.) A “missed connection” with a rogue insurance agent helping a customer and the resulting social media storm.</li>
<li><a href="https://dreamforge.mywebportal.app/dreamforge/stories/show/beyond-our-hidden-stars-sally-wiener-grotta">Beyond Our Hidden Stars, Sally Wiener Grotta</a> (Dreamforge 4) Finding hope in art when enslaved by a space corporation.</li>
<li><a href="https://dreamforge.mywebportal.app/dreamforge/stories/show/the-dryads-smile-h-orion-kim">The Dryad’s Smile, H. Orion Kim</a> (Dreamforge 5) The strength of relationships against otherworldy allures.</li>
<li><a href="https://dreamforge.mywebportal.app/dreamforge/stories/show/answered-prayers-scott-edelman">Answered Prayers, Scott Edelman</a> (Dreamforge 5) A magical bookstore of books never rewritten. A story about letting go.</li>
<li><a href="https://dreamforge.mywebportal.app/dreamforge/stories/show/climbing-the-motherman-henry-szabranski">Climbing the Motherman, Henry Szabranski</a> (Dreamforge 5) Living on a stone giant (cool world!), tribal power struggles, escaping disaster, protecting the weak.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><a href="https://firesidefiction.com/">Fireside</a></strong></p>
<p>Ha a focus on beautiful/lyrical writing.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://firesidefiction.com/object-permanence">Object Permanence, James Yu</a> (Fireside 2020/12.) Landmarks get social media accounts. Good, bad, and ugly at a conference. Romance.</li>
<li><a href="https://firesidefiction.com/the-intergalactic-shoemakers-revenge">The Intergalactic Shoemaker’s Revenge, Jordan Rivet</a> A nice tale of just deserts for a space pirate.</li>
<li><a href="https://firesidefiction.com/the-roman-road">The Roman Road, Vajra Chandrasekera</a> (Fireside, September 2020) Uploading, homunculi, capitalism.</li>
<li><a href="https://firesidefiction.com/redemption">Redemption, Mary Soon Lee</a> (Fireside, September 2020.) A beautiful story about the rhythm of imprisonment.</li>
<li><a href="https://firesidefiction.com/narrative-control">Narrative Control, Kyle Kirrin</a> (Fireside, October 2020.) Anxiety bot narrates your every fear. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YJg02ivYzSs&amp;feature=emb_logo">Hyper-reality</a>.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><a href="https://dailysciencefiction.com/">Daily Science Fiction</a></strong></p>
<p>Short, &lt;1000 words, good for a quick dose.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://dailysciencefiction.com/science-fiction/aliens/templeton-moss/meet-cute_Science_Fiction">Meet Cute, Templeton Moss</a> Alien romance. Delightful dialogue.</li>
<li><a href="http://dailysciencefiction.com/fantasy/modern-fantasy/thomas-j-griffin/naughty-list-4-lyfe">Naughty List 4 Lyfe, Thomas J. Griffin</a> (Daily Science Fiction, 2020/12/23.) Catch Santa and he’ll grant you a wish. But be careful what you wish for.</li>
<li><a href="http://dailysciencefiction.com/science-fiction/space-travel/tony-dunnell/generation-xmas">Generation Xmas, Tony Dunnell</a> (Daily Science Fiction, 2020/12/25.) When the adults try to bring Santa on board the space station, the kids have other ideas.</li>
<li><a href="https://dailysciencefiction.com/science-fiction/future-societies/matthew-sanborn-smith/you-will-find-yourself-buried-beneath-rubble">You Will Find Yourself Buried Beneath Rubble, Matthew Sanborn Smith</a> (Daily Science Fiction, 2020/11/20) Second-person, rapid-fire.</li>
<li><a href="https://dailysciencefiction.com/science-fiction/future-societies/elizabeth-a-terhune/teenage-neurogenesis">Teenage Neurogenesis, Elizabeth A Terhune</a> (Daily Science Fiction, Wednesday, October 14th, 2020.) “How would the workforce change if technology moved so quickly that teenagers–with their plastic minds–were the only ones who could fully understand the latest inventions?”</li>
</ul>

  </div>

    

    <!-- Extension : Sharing buttons @ www.sharethis.com -->
    <span class='st_facebook_large' displayText='Facebook'></span>
    <span class='st_twitter_large' displayText='Tweet'></span>
    <span class='st_googleplus_large' displayText='Google +'></span>
    <span class='st_reddit_large' displayText='Reddit'></span>
    <span class='st__large' displayText=''></span>

    <div id="disqus_thread"></div>
    


  
    <script>!function(d,s,id){var js,fjs=d.getElementsByTagName(s)[0],p=/^http:/.test(d.location)?'http':'https';if(!d.getElementById(id)){js=d.createElement(s);js.id=id;js.src=p+'://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js';fjs.parentNode.insertBefore(js,fjs);}}(document, 'script', 'twitter-wjs');</script>
  </div>
  
</div>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Readercon 2019</title>
    <link href="http://holdenlee.github.io/blog/posts/writing/readercon_2019.html" />
    <id>http://holdenlee.github.io/blog/posts/writing/readercon_2019.html</id>
    <published>2019-07-16T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2019-07-16T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[
<div class="container">
  <div id="content">
    <div class="page header">
      <h1>Readercon 2019</h1>
    </div>
    
    <div class="info">
       <div class="subtitle"><p>An inspiring experience</p></div> 
       
        <p>Posted: 2019-07-16 
          , Modified: 2019-07-16 
	</p>
      
       <p>Tags: <a href="/tags/writing.html">writing</a></p> 
    </div>
    
  </div>
  <!--/div-->

  <div class="toc"> <ul>
 <li><a href="#impressions">Impressions</a></li>
 <li><a href="#panels-and-talks">Panels and talks</a><ul>
 <li><a href="#the-21st-century-makeover-of-class-struggle-in-sff-fri.-11am">The 21st-Century Makeover of Class Struggle in SF/F (Fri. 11am)</a></li>
 <li><a href="#writing-craft-and-mentoring-programs-fri.-12pm">Writing craft and mentoring programs (Fri. 12pm)</a></li>
 <li><a href="#the-real-middle-ages-part-i-fri.-1pm">The Real Middle Ages, Part I (Fri. 1pm)</a></li>
 <li><a href="#latinx-authors-break-down-the-wall-fri.-2pm">Latinx authors break down the wall (Fri. 2pm)</a></li>
 <li><a href="#in-memoriam-gene-wolfe-fri.-3pm">In memoriam: Gene Wolfe (Fri. 3pm)</a></li>
 <li><a href="#why-does-space-get-the-opera-and-cyber-the-punk-fri.-4pm">Why Does Space Get the Opera and Cyber the Punk? (Fri. 4pm)</a></li>
 <li><a href="#talk-with-neil-clarke-fri.-7pm">Talk with Neil Clarke (Fri. 7pm)</a></li>
 <li><a href="#the-real-middle-ages-part-ii-sat.-11am">The Real Middle Ages, Part II (Sat. 11am)</a></li>
 <li><a href="#heist-stories-as-meta-genre-sat.-12pm">Heist stories as meta-genre (Sat. 12pm)</a></li>
 <li><a href="#marvelous-mundane-the-impossible-inadequate-40-minute-history-of-how-fiction-got-its-genres-sat.-2pm">Marvelous &amp; Mundane: The impossible, inadequate 40-minute history of how fiction got its genres (Sat. 2pm)</a></li>
 <li><a href="#how-we-write-this-is-how-you-lose-the-time-war-sat.-3pm">How we write “This is how you lose the time war” (Sat. 3pm)</a></li>
 <li><a href="#interview-stephen-graham-jones-sat.-4pm">Interview: Stephen Graham Jones (Sat. 4pm)</a></li>
 <li><a href="#hospitable-worlds-sat.-7pm">Hospitable Worlds (Sat. 7pm)</a></li>
 <li><a href="#how-much-science-is-enough-science-sat.-8pm">How much science is enough science? (Sat. 8pm)</a></li>
 <li><a href="#talk-with-jeanne-cavelos-inside-the-odyssey-workshop-sun.-10am-2pm">Talk with Jeanne Cavelos, Inside the Odyssey Workshop (Sun. 10am, 2pm)</a></li>
 <li><a href="#graybeards-beyond-gandalf-sun.-11am">Graybeards beyond Gandalf (Sun. 11am)</a></li>
 <li><a href="#making-first-contact-with-your-local-speculative-fiction-community-sun.-12pm">Making First Contact with Your Local Speculative Fiction Community (Sun. 12pm)</a></li>
 <li><a href="#from-seed-to-story-how-to-escape-the-slush-pile-sun.-1pm">From Seed to Story: How to Escape the Slush Pile (Sun. 1pm)</a></li>
 </ul></li>
 </ul> </div>

  <div class="blog-main">
    <p>I was at <a href="http://readercon.org">Readercon</a> in Boston this past Friday to Sunday (July 12-14). Readercon is a convention for “imaginative literature” (including science fiction, fantasy, and horror). I had an amazing time, and highly recommend it to anyone who reads or writes speculative fiction.</p>
<!-- http://www.readercon.org/media.htm -->
<p>Below, I’ll give some of my general impressions, as well as my notes on panels and talks.</p>
<p>Disclaimer: I’ve paraphrased the panel discussion and author talks, and apologize in advance for any mistakes or mis-representations (let me know by leaving a comment). The stuff that I included is what I personally found most interesting and could most easily lift out of my notes. There are plenty of other interesting things that I haven’t included.</p>
<p>Collected list of online resources: <a href="https://www.ralan.com/">Ralan.com (list of markets)</a>, <a href="http://www.odysseyworkshop.org/">Odyssey writing workshop</a>, <a href="https://writingtheother.com/">Writing the other</a>, <a href="http://critters.org/">Critters (online critique)</a>, <a href="https://www.codexwriters.com/">Codex writers (online critique and support)</a>.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.readercon.org/media.htm">Some media from Readercon</a>.</p>
<!-- Raw notes: https://workflowy.com/s/readercon-2019/q370VHlWycZSE0RK -->
<h2 id="impressions">Impressions</h2>
<p>I learned about Readercon from hanging out with the <a href="http://www.bsfwriters.com/">Brooklyn Speculative Fiction Writers</a>. This is the second science fiction/fantasy convention I’ve gone to. The first was WorldCon in London in 2014 (Loncon). I liked this a lot more because it was geared specifically towards the written word, and was a lot more intimate (with something like two or three hundred, rather than several thousand, people). I wish I had known about it ten years ago!</p>
<p>It’s especially a great experience for an aspiring writer, because you get to connect with the community as well as leave with tools to get better, ideas to pursue, and books to read. Coming back from Readercon I feel newly motivated to write.</p>
<p>I’ve found everyone really friendly, passionate, and dedicated to their work. I got to talk to Neil Clarke, editor of <a href="http://clarkesworldmagazine.com/">Clarkesworld magazine</a>, who was editor of the magazine for 13 years (while having a day job for the first 11 years) and goes through 1100 submissions a month; and Jeanne Cavelos, who went from astrophysicist to writer and spends a lot of time teaching writers through the <a href="http://www.odysseyworkshop.org/">Odyssey writing workshops</a>. I always imagined editors as hostile people in my head, but the opposite was true: they wouldn’t spend so much time on their job if they didn’t love their work, and they wanted to see writers succeed. Being rejected was an universal experience that people celebrated: authors talked about having a thousand rejection letters; editors expressed their delight at having someone succeed on the seventy-something try. Another universal was having to find the time and energy to write while having a job - whether it’s one that they’re equally invested in (I was cheered to see quite a few scientists!), a job just to make a living, or a job they would like to escape. Many people talked about having been mentored in their career, and feeling compelled to pass it on. There was an acknowledgement of the difficulty of making it, as well as an infectious determination to persevere.<a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"><sup>1</sup></a></p>
<p>Most of the panels were very high-quality. A lot of panels I went to talk about the existing literature around a certain theme, and how one might go beyond the tropes and stereotypes.<a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"><sup>2</sup></a> For example, the “real Middle Ages” are a lot more complex and varied than their homogeneous representation in medieval fantasy, and rather than young characters with ample time, what about lower-class characters or older characters (“graybeards beyond Gandalf”)? A convention is always very good for assembling a list of books to read and movies/shows to watch.</p>
<p>There were also author interviews, and talks about an author’s works. It’s great to listen to their journey of becoming a writer, and their approach to it. There was also lots of information about writing workshops and programs, as well as local and online communities.</p>
<!--


+ People are so friendly, passionate, dedicated. Editors and teachers. Editors are people too! Labor of love. Mentored by people, pass it on.
+ Rejection letters.
+ A lot of panels are about going beyond the tropes and stereotypes. 
+ Interviews and talks about specific authors.
+ 
-->
<!-- unfriendly in college-->
<!-- Stuff that I included is what I personally found most interesting. There were plenty of other interesting things that I haven't included.
-->
<h2 id="panels-and-talks">Panels and talks</h2>
<h3 id="the-21st-century-makeover-of-class-struggle-in-sff-fri.-11am">The 21st-Century Makeover of Class Struggle in SF/F (Fri. 11am)</h3>
<p><strong>Panelists:</strong> Malka Older, Sarah Smith, Cadwell Turnbull, Catherynne M. Valente, T.X. Watson (moderator)</p>
<p><strong>Description:</strong> With rising economic inequality and class struggle ever more visible in America, how are these issues being explored in SF/F? Is the pessimism of YA dystopias (from Suzanne Collins’s The Hunger Games, published at the start of the Great Recession, to M.T. Anderson’s Landscape with Invisible Hand in 2017) emblematic of changed views of the American Dream? How do recent works differ from their 20th-century forebears (Nancy Kress’s Beggars in Spain), and how are they tackling the intersection of class and other identities?</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> The need to have a hero in a story can bias a story towards middle and high-class characters, and means that a large portion of the human experience is left out. It is also not faithful to reality, because actual history is more often shaped by a large group of people rather than a single hero. Many mundane acts of heroism are also systematically ignored.</p>
<p>Stories have to follow individual characters, but we can show them embedded in their organizations or communities and focus more on those dynamics. Stories need to be engaging, but that also means we can talk about difficult issues through “vampires and robots.”</p>
<p>The stories that we consume affect the way that we see the world, for example, through hero worship. It’s a double-edged sword. <!-- This turned into a discussion about how --></p>
<p><strong>Highlights from panel discussion:</strong></p>
<p>CV: As genres, science fiction and fantasy often have trouble dealing with class because the hero is often the one who has enough spare time to pursue a plot or mystery. People who are not part of the elite (e.g., the nobility or technical elite) don’t have time to figure out what’s going on, only the time to face things as they come. Fantasy especially has trouble with this because the nobility are the “movers and shakers of history”; at best you get the middle class (“fat hobbits”).</p>
<p>CT: A novel has to follow a person or small group to some climax, but actual history is seldom shaped by a few people. It’s more often shaped by a large group, including many people who don’t get named. Speculative fiction could do a lot to explore movements: how large groups of people work together to change society. The Dispossessed by Ursula Le Guin does a good job.</p>
<p>MO: We act as if we’re past monarchy, but a lot of things in our world came from the Victorian age. For example, breakfast buffets in hotels are an aristocratic tradition.</p>
<p>CV: We are still in a oligarchy; we are in a new gilded age. We have been “convinced as a culture to cheerlead capitalism, and specific players in capitalism.” Consider how much geek fandom is invested in the Avengers endgame. Disney doesn’t care about us! Media companies are making a ridiculous amount of money convincing us to consume their stuff as a fun hobby. Corporations are “making us complicit in our own oppression, and [making us] find it entertaining.”</p>
<p>SS: It’s difficult to write a book about work, and about how politics works at a ground level. I think we can write more interesting novels if we can concentrate on how economic systems really work.</p>
<p><em>Question: How do you address the fundamental difficulty that stories have to be about individual people, not about systems?</em></p>
<p>MO: I’m fascinated by organizations, and group dynamics. Working as part of an organization, you can see yourself as a hero for a certain amount of time, but after a while you can’t keep tricking yourself. In stories, you need characters to identify with; I can’t be intrigued by abstractions. But we can show characters enmeshed in the organizations they’re working for.</p>
<p>In the modern world we consume a lot of content. If I don’t have a stack of good stories within easy reach I get nervous. Consuming this much affects how our brains mediate the world, and frames our experiences. We put the popular narratives as frames on everything we see. This can both be a good and bad thing.</p>
<p>We imagine people as heroes, because plots are built around individual heroes. We imagine romance where there isn’t any. What we think of as fundamental aspects of story are not fundamental - they’ve changed over history. Sometimes we’re right because others act on the same impulses, and so the story sense is a kind of intuition, but sometimes it’s false. We need to be critical of the narratives we’re consuming and imagining.</p>
<p>CV: We are motivated to take the stories we read and bring them into the real world. Consider the amount of worship that people direct towards Elon Musk, Donald Trump, and other billionaires. Trump is a “real world Tony Stark” (from Iron Man). We want to live in a world where someone comes to save the day. Elon Musk has been terrible for the class struggle; he was born with privilege upon privilege; his claimed inventions aren’t invented by him. But he bends narrative energy towards him, so people see him as a way to live in a different story.</p>
<p>CT: There’s a drive towards exceptionalism in stories: a super-competent hero saves the day. A challenge is to write normal people, facing something traumatic in their normal lives.</p>
<p>MO: Consider people who are heroes in your and other people’s lives. It’s hard to find these heroes in the news; they are unknown or disappear immediately; it’s hard to anchor them in your head. <!--If we really look, there is so much heroism by people who are unknown, or quickly disappear.--> The things we are told are heroic are not as heroic or exciting as the things we ignore completely.</p>
<p>For example, pregnancy and childbirth are largely ignored in science fiction. But pregnancy is a heroic journey, and much more guaranteed to have pain than the journey of throwing a ring in the volcano. We think of it as mundane, unexciting, unremarkable. But this kind of heroism doesn’t have to be boring - think about the struggle to feed one’s family.</p>
<p>CV: Pregnancy shows up in horror stories. But childbirth and early childrearing are ignored, and used as a way to get rid of a woman character.</p>
<p>Breastfeeding is a class marker that has switched. It used to be that wealthy people used baby formula; breastfeeding was seen as vulgar and obscene. Now, it’s wealthy women who have the time to breastfeed, and the poor who use a formula because they have to go back to work.</p>
<p>Even women don’t write about these things because they think it’s not novel-worthy. Similarly, war is worthy and education is not. (Though, education and childrearing are talked about in AI stories.)</p>
<p>There is nothing in life that class does not permeate. Art has no obligation but to tell the truth, but if you are not involving class you are probably not telling the truth.</p>
<p><em>Question: We eat nutritious food (stories tackling important issues) and pizza (popular fiction). Where capitalism booms, are we doomed to pizza?</em></p>
<p>CT: Spinach pizza? If you create a beautiful thing, you can sneak in a lot of cool stuff and people will support it.</p>
<p>CV: This is where science fiction and fantasy shine. We can write about class struggle with vampires and robots. It’s not fun without vampires and robots, because we read about it in the newspaper every day. But because we write in genres, it goes down easier, in a way that people will remember more, because they were not expecting to get a lecture on class struggle.</p>
<p>MO: Fun is a highly underrated quality in literature. Writing about class, slavery, etc. doesn’t have to contradict fun; the writing and voice can be strong and enjoyable.</p>
<p><em>Q: Does human nature make utopia impossible?</em></p>
<p>CT: We need to get away from merit-based systems. The punishment for not winning the cherry-pie-eating contest should not be abject poverty. The bottom line should be nice and solid, so no one is falling through it.</p>
<p>MO: There are many ways to organize society. We’ve designed society to incentivize certain ways of sucking. There are new societies we haven’t tried yet. We won’t know until we go out and try.</p>
<h3 id="writing-craft-and-mentoring-programs-fri.-12pm">Writing craft and mentoring programs (Fri. 12pm)</h3>
<p><strong>Panelists:</strong> Jack Dann, Theodora Goss (moderator), Kate Maruyama, Kenneth Schneyer, Holly Walrath</p>
<p><strong>Description:</strong> Those who want to learn the craft of writing popular genre fiction have more options then ever. MFA programs and workshops of excellent repute are popping up all over the U.S., from Stonecoast in Maine to Clarion in California, as well as in other parts of the world. With so many options, how does one choose? Panelists who have participated in these programs as mentors or mentees will discuss their experiences.</p>
<p><strong>Summary:</strong> The panelists compared credentialing programs (such as MFA’s) with intensive workshops. Intensive workshops develop critiquing facilities that you can turn onto your own work, as well as create instant community and give you a mutual support system. A credentialing program won’t do more for your editing skills than a workshop will, but is important if you want to teach writing. A degree program is like an apprenticeship; pay attention to who you’re going to be studying with, and whether they are good teachers. There are a variety of different programs, from full-time to low-residency programs.</p>
<p>Beyond the high-profile workshops, there are many local workshops and classes, for example, <a href="https://grubstreet.org/">Grub Street</a> in Boston and <a href="https://www.writingclasses.com/">Gotham Writers</a> in New York, as well as online classes such as <a href="http://www.odysseyworkshop.org/">Odyssey</a> and <a href="https://writingtheother.com/">Writing the Other</a>. Recommendations for books on writing: <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/68024.Steering_the_Craft">Steering the Craft, Ursula Le Guin</a> and <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/48654.Story">Story, Robert McKee</a>. <!-- beyond high-profile workshops: local workshops and classes. online classes, talk and share. Boston Webb street. NY Gotham writers. Odyssey online classes. Writing the other. 
inspiration2pub.com --> <!-- JY 2 book props rejected today --></p>
<p>KS: Rejection is part of an artists’ life; be accustomed to the experience without being crushed. I’m reasonably successful, and my acceptance rate is 9%. Get used to resending things.</p>
<!-- HW: Ursula Le Guin's steering the craft
JD: Story, McKee-->
<h3 id="the-real-middle-ages-part-i-fri.-1pm">The Real Middle Ages, Part I (Fri. 1pm)</h3>
<p><strong>Panelists:</strong> Charles Allison, Robert Killheffer, Chelsea R. Miller (moderator), Jess Nevins, Faye Ringel</p>
<p><strong>Description:</strong> Medieval Europe was a hotbed of interaction among people of different cultures and ethnicities, so there’s no reason for fantasy novels with medieval-like settings to be blandly homogeneous. Panelists will discuss how popular narratives of medieval Europe misrepresent known history, how these narratives serve white supremacist movements, and how writers can do better by readers by basing their worldbuilding on Europe as it really was.</p>
<p><strong>Highlights from panel discussion:</strong></p>
<p><em>Inventing the narrative of the Middle Ages</em></p>
<p>CA: The image of Europe as a sequestered place during the Middle Ages, not influenced by other lands, is absurd. A simple version of history is an agenda.</p>
<p>CM: Medievalism in pop culture tells us less about medieval world, and more about the ecology where it’s written. Check out <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/35543040-medievalism-in-a-song-of-ice-and-fire-and-game-of-thrones">Shiloh Carroll’s book on medievalism in A Song of Ice and Fire</a>. <!-- CM: Shylo Carol' examines medievalism in Song of Ice and Fire - writers and directors fall into traditional views and tropes #book --></p>
<p>FR: The Middle Ages is always being reinvented to mirror what people are looking for at the time. The very idea of “middle” started as pejorative. It was coined during the Italian Renaissance, to imply all the “middle” stuff between them the Roman empire was bad.</p>
<p>On the flip side, countries often use their “history” in the middle ages for the sake of nation-building, for example, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kalevala">Kalevala</a> from Finland.</p>
<p>CA: Saying that Mongols are oppressors is a simplistic narrative. A lot of Russian and Muscovite culture comes from Mongol/steppe influence. As James Halper said, even hostilities require a degree of intimacy. “You sacrifice accuracy for a narrative you find compelling… Fantasy is a key part of history.”</p>
<p>RK: Rulers create backstories for their countries to legitimize their rule. The idea of “national types/characters” is that the place a person is from tells you something about them.</p>
<p>CM: There is a history of European national leaders abusing their historical stories for nationalistic purposes. For example, Francesco Franco invoked the memory of Spain’s medieval past.</p>
<p>JN: Check out the book <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/351753.Inventing_the_Middle_Ages">Inventing the middle ages</a>. <!--One thing Tolkien emphasized--></p>
<p>RK: Mythmaking is not unique to 19th century Europe. Early Anglo-Saxons rulers made up genealogies to include Jesus and Caesar.</p>
<!-- https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/News_from_Nowhere-->
<p>CA: Europe got heavy cavalry from steppe cultures. This runs counter to the standard white nationalist narrative of a sequestered Europe.</p>
<p><em>CM: What ways are white supremacist transforming the past? What are ways writers and readers can respond?</em></p>
<p>FR: The name King Arthur Flour came from the association of medievalism with whiteness, purity, and strength. The KKK saw themselves as descendants of noble Scots clans and dressed with what they imagined as 15th and 16th century clothes.</p>
<p>JN: The white nationalist website Stormfront gives a history of the white race, leaving out everyone who’s not white; it constructs a reactionary version of the middle ages. The son of the cofounder read up on the middle ages and defected from his family and the movement, getting a degree in medieval studies.</p>
<p>RK: Respond using facts! Anyone open to facts will have to change their mind; facts overwhelm simplistic stories.</p>
<p>CA: Check out primary sources from other countries interacting with medieval Europe. A great book is <a href="https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/316708/the-ultimate-ambition-in-the-arts-of-erudition-by-shihab-al-din-al-nuwayri-edited-translated-and-with-an-introduction-and-notes-by-elias-muhanna/9780143107484/">The Ultimate Ambition in the Arts of Erudition by Al-Nuwayri</a>. Open to any page and it’s fascinating; you see a historical account of a battle, or how to cure a hangover, or erotic poetry next to an article denouncing erotic poetry.</p>
<p><em>Q: Tell us about another culture that has interacted with medieval Europe.</em></p>
<p>FR: I want to point out the Jewish contribution. When I was starting grad school, nobody was writing about it. There are huge amounts waiting for translation to be accessible, such as the Yiddish King Arthur story, and the story of the Jewish troubadours.</p>
<p>RK: Arabic literature had a large influence. Research in the 1990’s and 2000’s revealed the extent of the interaction.</p>
<p>JN: I’m fascinated with individuals who cross borders. In 1102, a Sudanese man accompanied crusaders to North France, and became the hangman of Lyon, France. He was even more <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Black_Adder">Black Adder</a> than Black Adder. The crusader was killed by a mob, and there was no evidence of what happened to the hangman (named John). He was wandering around Northern France. Someone needs to write this story!</p>
<p>CM: I like to focus on places with intercultural interactions, like the Mediterranean and North Africa.</p>
<h3 id="latinx-authors-break-down-the-wall-fri.-2pm">Latinx authors break down the wall (Fri. 2pm)</h3>
<!-- The panelists talked about their own experiences in growing up, their experiences of racism towards or within the Latinx community, and about the history of immigration to the US. Finally, they talked about the role of fiction in helping break those stereotypes.-->
<p><strong>Panelists:</strong> Lisa Bradley (moderator), Carlos Hernandez, José Pablo Iriarte, Julia Rios</p>
<!--, Sabrina Vourvoulias-->
<p><strong>Description:</strong> Isolationist governments portray immigrants (and citizens perceived as foreigners) as vectors for disease, crime, and terrorism. Currently, the U.S. administration is demonizing Latinx immigrants in this fashion, and oppressing asylum-seekers from Central America. How can authors dismantle anti-immigrant myths while portraying immigrants in all their human complexity? Led by Lisa M. Bradley, Latinx writers will discuss their work regarding borders and immigration, providing historical context and exploring possibilities for future stories.</p>
<p><strong>Highlights from panel discussion:</strong></p>
<p>CH: After Fidel Castro took power, the US had the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wet_feet,_dry_feet_policy">wet foot dry foot</a> policy: If a Cuban could put one foot on American soil, they were allowed in and embraced, and if they were caught on the strait, they were sent back. (The policy was recently rescinded by the Obama administration.) After Castro came to power, Cubans went from being perceived as exotic like other Caribbean people, to being perceived as freedom fighters. This gave Cubans a position of privilege compared to other Latin Americans, though they still faced racism.</p>
<p>White is not a color; it is an ideological position. The Irish were not considered white for a long time.</p>
<p>JPI: There are differences in status within the Miami Cuban population - people divided themselves based on who had left the country earlier.</p>
<p>JR: My father is from Mexico, but in our family we internalized the idea that the best way to be successful is to be as white as possible. My parents didn’t want to teach us Spanish. My dad wanted me to know my heritage without being part of it.</p>
<p><em>LB: Where we settle in the US has an effect on how we’re treated.</em></p>
<p>CH: Florida is its own brand of weird - ask Google to auto-complete “A Florida man.” I grew up in Sarasota. The average age is deceased (older than the average life expectancy). It is the high school drinking capital. People there have set up microwalls with each other. There is homophobia and different levels of racism based on skin color.</p>
<p>JR: There’s a difference between rural and urban communities. Los Angeles has a giant Mexican population, with more Mexican-Americans than whites, but it still feeds to white privilege.</p>
<p>Urban communities benefit from having a big community, through having newspapers, festivals, and activism. We moved to rural Southern California. It is very red and has a significant Latinx population, much of which was farm workers. White people own farms, and Latinx people work.</p>
<p>I picked strawberries in the summer. Latinx workers were devalued and paid little. People who were much better at picking than me may have been paid less because the owners thought I was white. <!--Urban - more community, ex. Opinión newspaper, festivals, etc. --></p>
<p><em>LB: Children of immigrants are part of two different cultures. What kinds of conflicts and identity issues arise?</em></p>
<p>JPI: I keep writing about children of immigrants “stuck between two cultures.” We are expected to honor our heritage, but it conflicts with the dominant culture. I grew up in the “shadow of Havana,” in its re-creation in Florida. I have never been to Cuba, and if I traveled there, it would be as a tourist, but I feel a loyalty to the culture, and obligations to the land. <!-- I never stepped foot on. If I traveled there, I would travel as a tourist.--></p>
<p>CH: I visited Cuba in 1997 as part of an educational exchange, and brought back $200 worth of cuban cigars, legally. I saw the devastation of Havana. It looks like a slow-motion bombing had happened over four decades. The Cuba that existed is preserved in Miami now - the idealistic version, with money. It’s said that the “three failures” of the revolution are breakfast, lunch, and dinner.</p>
<p>JR: I’m half-Mexican; my mother is white and Protestant. I didn’t fit with either side of my family.</p>
<p>People who spoke Spanish as their first language were often defensive, lashing out at anyone who doesn’t speak Spanish. When you feel powerless, you gain the only power you can, by lashing out at other people.</p>
<p>I took Spanish in high school. My father yelled at me when I made mistakes; I had a big mental block from learning the language for a long time.</p>
<p>JR: My ideal world is a world without borders. Open borders create economic prosperity. After Brexit, people didn’t actually want to leave, because no other deal looks good; they need immigrants for industry.</p>
<p>There was a community meeting on immigration policies in Somerville. The major said: we love immigrants, and we need you to work in the hotel and casino that’s opening. The meaning was: We want you here - and out of sight.</p>
<p>JR: We need fiction showing Latinx characters being human, and we need a variety of voices, for a chorus effect.</p>
<p>JPI: Studies show that readers are more capable of empathy; they learn to live outside themselves. Marginalized communities get value from seeing themselves in print. Non-marginalized readers get value fromn seeing us in print and identifying with us.</p>
<p>JR: People change when they see others who don’t seem to share an identity with - <!--they don't think they share an identity with,--> and then see themselves in those people.</p>
<p>CH: Fiction plays the long game. A book here now can keep talking 75 years from now, reverberating and inspiring others to write things.</p>
<p>There are things to work on inside our communities: the bullshit machismo that permeates the culture, homophobia, and position against women. I grew up on the show Salvador Gigante, which had naked women dancing around onstage.</p>
<p>JPI: Criticism is easier to take from people within the community.</p>
<p>JR: Racism is not just a problem in the US; it’s also in Latinx countries. When a country is colonized, being like the colonizer is ideal, so people prized whiteness. “Limpia de la sangre,” purity of the blood, is racism based on how much Spanish/Indio heritage one has.</p>
<p>Check out <a href="https://www.legendofpolloman.com/">Polloman</a>, a Mexican mythology comic.</p>
<h3 id="in-memoriam-gene-wolfe-fri.-3pm">In memoriam: Gene Wolfe (Fri. 3pm)</h3>
<p><strong>Panelists:</strong> John Clute, C.S.E. Cooney, Chris Gerwel, Elizabeth Hand (moderator), Howard Waldrop</p>
<p><strong>Description:</strong> Gene Wolfe (1931–2019) was Readercon’s first guest of honor, and for good reason. His Book of the New Sun series was not so much groundbreaking as earth-shattering; his short fiction equally displayed his virtuoso talent for unsettling and disorienting the reader. He dipped into numerous genres and refused to be bound by the conventions of any. Join us to remember our friend and colleague and to explore his extraordinary body of work.</p>
<p><strong>Highlights from panel discussion:</strong></p>
<p>CG: I first encountered Gene Wolfe’s books as a kid, when I was 10 years old. I got it because it had a fantasy-looking cover, and understood 1/4 of it. It was dense, interesting fantasy, unlike any other. There was more I didn’t grasp. I keep going back to it, seeing more layers to how he’s constructing narratives. It boils down to layers and contradictions.</p>
<p>JC: Reading the Book of the Citadel, his masterpiece, was like falling down a rabbit-hole, opening a door into something that had no bottom. You had to read every single word, and believe. When you believe every word, then there are no deceptions. At the end, everything is true. After all the meanness and cruelty, this torturer [the main character] was searching for some way to become a good person.</p>
<p>CC: Because I wanted to be a writer, my father introduced me to Gene Wolfe, who was in the same church. He was twinkly-eyed and friendly, a raconteur. You have to start by writing short stories, he said, they can be about anything.</p>
<p>He became a mentor to me. We exchanged letters; he took me to brunch, to conventions, taught me to write cover letters. I wrote to him about my rejections, and he said, good on you for moaning. Shouting to the walls is even better. “It is those who say it doesn’t matter who cannot be saved.” I kept my rejection slips with his letters.</p>
<p><em>EH: Wolfe was a convert to Catholicism. He said Catholicism was impossible to keep out of his work, but it’s not easy to pick up the clues. How and should it matter?</em></p>
<p>CG: One can read his work without any awareness of his faith, but his faith permeates it at every level. For example, he would reference theological debates in Catholic tradition, like some schism in the 12th century. His work always had a drive towards goodness, an optimism, a quest to positive morality, which set it apart from the modernist tradition.</p>
<p>JC: Every moment has been his drive to do the right thing. Gene Wolfe’s protagonists are young boys, but his books are not YA novels. In the end, the ideal Gene Wolfe character fulfilling Gene Wolfe goodness is a boy managing to do a man’s work.</p>
<p>EH: Rather than invent a new language, Wolfe would mine the English language, and create an ornate style out of the strangeness of the English language. He cast a big shadow over genre writers.</p>
<p>HW: I’ve never consciously tried to imitate Wolfe. His writing is so changeable. He writes a story like it needs to be written. It’s impossible to imitate one-off person. The way he could craft the story once he had the setup - he did exactly what story needed. I try to do the same thing: never write the same story twice, never write the kind of story from the same viewpoint twice. It feels like the story was there, Gene Wolfe just wrote it down. <!--Only achieve after done so many times. --></p>
<p>CC: I started writing short stories. He would comment on them, “prose like uncooked dumplings but the dialogue is pretty good.” At 18, I wrote to him for any response. I kept submitting stories, but didn’t get accepted.</p>
<p>I was also writing story poems. He said that they were very good - use the poetic structure, keep every line, just put it in paragraph form. It got published in Subterranean Press. It gave me permission, that a short story can be rich.</p>
<p>JC: Gene Wolfe is the most emotionally intense writer I’ve encountered. The more you get to the center of Wolfe, the quieter it gets: Dead silence at the center of the most impassionate heat. His books are complex; you have to go through the carapace to the truth he’s telling. He is exposing and defending himself at same time.</p>
<p>CG: There is a large amount of work the reader is expected to bring to his stories. One can project just about any kind of emotional impact or meaning onto a Gene Wolfe story. What he is asking us to do is to think about it, to construct a response to his work for ourselves.</p>
<h3 id="why-does-space-get-the-opera-and-cyber-the-punk-fri.-4pm">Why Does Space Get the Opera and Cyber the Punk? (Fri. 4pm)</h3>
<p><strong>Panelists:</strong> Liz Gorinsky, Austin Grossman, Catherynne M. Valente, Sabrina Vourvoulias, T.X. Watson (moderator)</p>
<p><strong>Description:</strong> For Arisia’s 50 Panels in 75 Minutes panel in 2018, Cecilia Tan suggested “Why Does Space Get the Opera and Cyber the Punk?”, which was universally acclaimed as too good for 1.5 minutes. Our panelists will give this exploration of speculative and musical genres the full hour it deserves. (And where is the spacepunk and cyber opera?)</p>
<p><strong>Highlights from panel discussion:</strong></p>
<p><em>Thoughts on punk vs. opera</em></p>
<p>AG: “Space opera” was coined in the 40’s as a derogatory term - operas are boring. It’s more what people thought about operas.</p>
<p>CV: “Punk” was also derogatory.</p>
<p>AM: It’s more about the aesthetics than about the musical genre. My initial understanding of “space opera” was that it’s space books written by women with emotion. [cf. soap opera]</p>
<!-- cyberpunk is actually electronica/industrial music-->
<p>CV: It’s a lot to do with class. Cyberpunk is about people not in the ruling class, while space opera is (it takes money to go to space).</p>
<p>AM: Opera is enjoyed by the upper classes, and a symbol of decadent elitism. It describes a story that has an over-the-top grand narrative, involving people with the time and energy to go on adventures.</p>
<p>CV: Most people don’t like opera but think they should. It’s not an art form for the mainstream. Punk is music, aesthetic, feeling, and culture; it speaks to people.</p>
<p><em>Catherynne Valente on <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/24100285-space-opera">Space Opera</a> and Eurovision</em></p>
<p>Quote: “the only wall we could ever build against What’s Going On was the glitter and the shine and the synth and the knowing grin that never stops knowing. The show. Because the opposite of fascism isn’t anarchy, it’s theater.”</p>
<p>CV: The book is a love letter to music, based off Eurovision; it’s a working-class space opera. Eurovision is a nationalistic project.</p>
<p>Costumes are a big part of Eurovision, representing the culture of the country. Iceland’s band had the goal of ending capitalism. They sang “Hatred will prevail” and never broke character. Everyone hated them but the American media thought they were adorable.</p>
<p><em>More optimistic visions?</em></p>
<p>AM: The inheritors of the anxiety of cyberpunk are climate/ecological science fiction.</p>
<p>TXW: Solarpunk gives an optimistic view of the near future, taking into account the environmental realities of the present; it’s a reaction to dystopia. Dystopia is a fire alarm, useful if there’s a path out; otherwise it just makes burning to death worse.</p>
<p>AM: I like Christian sacred harp music. There’s an Appalachian folk tradition, sung in 4 parts. The participants are untrained. They sing in a square, at each other. It’s not for an audience, but for participants. It’s gender neutral, and can be sung in any octave. The lyrics are based on apolistic Christian hymns from the 18th century. What would the soundtrack to climate fuction be? That with electronic voices.</p>
<p><em>Some recommendations:</em></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Feed_(Anderson_novel)">Feed, MT Anderson</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/series/170872-wayfarers">Wayfarers, Becky Chambers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/44438351-architects-of-memory?ac=1&amp;from_search=true">Architect of memory, Karen Osborne</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/43462058-expanse-series-1-6?ac=1&amp;from_search=true">Expanse series</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6m1O5i6oUTI">ONE by Yeasayer (music video)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/22320.Pattern_Recognition?ac=1&amp;from_search=true">Pattern Recognition, William Gibson</a></li>
</ul>
<!--
AM: What would a working-class story about being in space look like?

AM: We do have books like that. Some of William Gibson's stories in space feels like spacepunk, for example [The Hinterlands](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hinterlands_(short_story)), where everyone who comes back from a wormhole commits suicide.

LG: Joy is not in the palette of punk.

AM: It's not so much joy as viciousness.

CV: Feed, MT Anderson. Tech is woven in the teen experience, taking it away is dystopic. In punk, tech has to be a little evil.

AM: not enough on aesthetics, fashion, food, visual signalling. 

CV: Costumes are a big part of Eurovision, representing the culture of the country. Iceland's band had the goal of ending capitalism. They sang "Hatred will prevail" and never broke character. Everyone hated them but the American media thought they were adorable.

AG: It's easier to imagine the end of the world than capitalism.
-->
<h3 id="talk-with-neil-clarke-fri.-7pm">Talk with Neil Clarke (Fri. 7pm)</h3>
<p><em>On managing slush readers:</em></p>
<p>Neil Clarke guides slush readers one-on-one during their first month. Any story that they pass up to him, he gives feedback if he doesn’t end up taking it. The comments in the internal system are brutally honest.</p>
<p>Everyone starts by recommending more stories than they should, but they soon adjust. Reading the slush pile can give people a confidence boost - they see they are better than x% of the slush.</p>
<p>People make routine mistakes; it’s easy to catch in someone else’s writing.</p>
<!-- read magazine 6 months -->
<p><em>On being an editor:</em></p>
<p>Clarke reads 1100-1200 stories a month, and is first reader on 70% of submissions. A slush reader has to read 5 stories a day. It sounds like a lot, but you don’t have to read all of a story - you can pick up on clues to reject.</p>
<p>For 11 out of 13 years, he did this while holding a day job.</p>
<p>The really bad stories are the easiest to reject. The hardest are the stories that are good until they blow the ending. <!-- char out of char, rules of world don't apply anymore--></p>
<p>For an issue, he picks stories that work well together, like a mixtape.</p>
<p>Every editor wants to discover a new author.</p>
<!-- cover letter - something of them representative in story. ex. based on family. then know what talk about -->
<p>People read a magazine because their tastes are similar to the editor’s. Often when the editor changes, the magazine loses readership, not because it’s gotten worse, but because it’s gone in a different direction.</p>
<p>Some of the best storytelling is when you have a 5000-word story, but you swear it’s 8000-10000. It’s a well-designed universe, so that everyone can fill in the gaps.</p>
<!-- when short story is chapter of novel, pains me to say it should be novel
best storytelling - 5000 word story, you swear it's 8000-10000. You fill in gaps, well-designed universe, everyone else can fill in.
Average person who goes to con and workshop is in top 70%,
When stop horror, hate mail go down. 
7 years ago, heart attack at readercon. Took years to accept, I can't enjoy horror because I've seen enough.
-->
<p><em>Data insights</em></p>
<p>Years ago, when the submission numbers were lower, Clarke did some research on demographics. 70% of submissions came from men and 30% from women, but of accepted stories, 40% were from men and 60% from women.</p>
<p>He gave out a survey to 1000 of the authors, asking them to read the five authors that most influenced them. He found that he was more likely to publish people who read authors he was unfamiliar with, and women were more likely to read different authors from him. <!-- Ursula Le Guin, Ray bradbury, Stephen King were common and good--> The lesson is that reading broadly works. The more sources you can pull from, the less likely you’ll write something the editor has seen before.</p>
<!-- pick stories that work well together, like a mixtape-->
<p>There are people who don’t get published until their 70th submission.</p>
<p>Clarke has a spreadsheet of every story, and tracks the demographics. When he publishes a story from a foreign country, the readership and submissions from that country spikes. He also has report cards for each slush reader.</p>
<h3 id="the-real-middle-ages-part-ii-sat.-11am">The Real Middle Ages, Part II (Sat. 11am)</h3>
<p><strong>Panelists:</strong> Charles Allison, Carolyn Ives Gilman, Anna Kashina (moderator), Chelsea R. Miller, Walt Williams</p>
<p><strong>Description:</strong> Writers looking for alternatives to cod-medieval European settings don’t need to look far. The years 500 to 1500 C.E. were times of tremendous cultural and technological change around the world. Novelties of that period included Islam, paper money, and fast-ripening rice; the Incan Empire, Great Zimbabwe, and the Tang Dynasty flourished. Which non-European settings of the 6th to 16th centuries have been successfully used as the basis for fantasy lands, and which might writers find particularly inspiring?</p>
<p><strong>Highlights from Panel Discussion:</strong></p>
<p>CG: The origin of science fiction and fantasy can be traced to travel literature of the Elizabethan era; it similarly evoked a sense of wonder.</p>
<p><em>Some non-European settings</em></p>
<p>CA: There is a range of contradictions and varieties in a small area. For example, going from Yucatan to the border with Texas:</p>
<ul>
<li>The Maya in Yucatan had the <em>milpa</em> system of farming; it’s the only sustainable way to farm with thin topsoil atop permeable limestone permeable, and it still persists now.</li>
<li>The Aztecs (?) had an urban empire in tune with the environment. Cortés wrote about a city twice as big as Madrid and clean, with free education.</li>
<li>The Chichimecas are nomadic hunter-gatherers, semi-pastoralists, who fought a 50-year long guerrilla war with the Spanish despite being relatively stone-age people.</li>
</ul>
<p>CG: There is an amazing enchanted landscape, with ruins old as the Roman empire, enormous geometrical symbols on the landscape. When you walk across it you can’t see the other end. They reproduced the same designs hundreds of miles apart, patterns of circles and squares. It’s the fabled land of Ohio! <!--Indian mounds.--> These are symbols from a people fascinated with geometry and measurements. They knew math and astronomy. What message were they sending? It’s a marvelous mystery.</p>
<!-- https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/17928971-the-garden-at-the-roof-of-the-world?ac=1&from_search=true-->
<p><em>How do you approach research?</em></p>
<p>WW: I look at the literature of people I’m writing about. This gives the internal view. I recommend Cynthia Ward and Nisi Shawl’s book <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/1760104.Writing_the_Other?ac=1&amp;from_search=true">Writing the Other</a>.</p>
<p>CM: Stay abreast of recent scholarship. Folks are trying to make it broadly accessible.</p>
<p>CG: There is no substitute for visiting the people themselves. Find differences in attitudes, in the way people look at the world. <!-- It frames what you're thinking in a different way.--></p>
<p>CG: Non-western civilizations have different ways of telling stories, different narrative structure and language; it’s non-Aristotelian. Western readers find it deeply unsatisfying. Just by transforming them to stories satisfying to Western readers, we are distorting and colonizing them.</p>
<p>CG (?): My research is on Brazil. I find a ton of stuff searching in Portuguese on YouTube. People film their local festivals. At the local market there will be someone selling DVD’s. They’re wicked good. <!-- 
CA: Max Gladstone's Craft sequence, Meso-american. Capitalism kills 9/10 of gods. Corporate ownership and human sacrifice. #book 
WW: (?), India, Nepal, Himalayas, Middle East. Ian MacDonald, ... god. ..., The Story of the Stone #book 
CG: Marlin James, Red Leopard Black Wolf #book 
CM: The City of Brass, Chakraborty, 18th C Ottoman Cairo #book 
AK: A hundred thousand kingdoms, N.K. Jemisin - based on Hinduism. Original. Amos Tutula (?), African folklore #book 
--></p>
<h3 id="heist-stories-as-meta-genre-sat.-12pm">Heist stories as meta-genre (Sat. 12pm)</h3>
<p><strong>Panelists:</strong> Josh Jasper, John P. Murphy (moderator), Tracy Townsend, John Wiswell, Navah Wolfe</p>
<p><strong>Description:</strong> On a panel at Readercon 29 about collaboration and community, John Wiswell observed that heist novels have “a synthesis of premise and plot,” while Scott Lynch added that heist stories reinforce that people need one another. This panel will dig more into heist stories, which (like humor and horror) can be layered on top of any genre or setting. What makes them satisfying? How can they make use of speculative elements while retaining their core of human ingenuity and interdependence?</p>
<p><strong>Highlights from Panel Discussion:</strong></p>
<p><em>JM: What is it about committing crimes that is so fun? How to write heists in a speculative environment? What does “synthesis of premise and plot” mean?</em></p>
<p>JW: A heist story focuses on a group rather than individual (and it counters our toxic individualism). Heists can only function if you assemble a group. Heists were originally wedded to the crime or police procedural genre. But it’s a schemata that can be placed over any genre, doing what the premise of the genre asks you to do. If you want to steal the king’s treasure, you can make it a heist rather than through battle as a knight. <!--Many genres can use this plot formula. --></p>
<p>NW: It’s a worldbuilding tool. Use it to explore. Going from A to B to C, you can fill in out the world. <!--pulling in all elements.--></p>
<p>TT: It allows us to participate in a crime as a proxy. There are many stories about trickster-like figures: Coyote, Anansi, Loki. But it always ends badly for Anansi - it’s not individuals but groups who are successful, like Robin Hood and his merry men.</p>
<p>JJ: Heist stories require the reader to accept the rejection of the law. It requires society to be unfair. Heist stories are good when I don’t want to read about a revolution, I want to read about someone stealing for themself.</p>
<p>NW: You have to define the bad guy as the person you’re stealing from.</p>
<p><em>Heros in heists</em></p>
<p>TT: We think of heists as plotty, but actually we have to think explicitly about character and motive. (JW: See Republic of Thieves - it’s the second level of heist fiction, the reveal isn’t how, but why.)</p>
<p>NW: The audience will support lots of things. There is nothing as sexy as extreme competence. Bring together highly competent people, and I will follow you down any dark road, as long as it’s fun. Heists are competence porn.</p>
<p>JJ: There is a genre-related desire to see super-competent people. We (fans) are encouraged to see ourselves as smart people, solving things with our brains. Even the punchy guy super-competent about punchy. We want to see ourselves in the heist.</p>
<p><em>Group dynamics:</em></p>
<p>TT: (asks people who play tabletop RPG to raise their hands) RPG’s are like heists; players have narrow competence growing over time, and need each other. It’s wonderfully deep Platonic bonding.</p>
<p>Heist stories are love stories - about found family - We’re in this together because we have to be.</p>
<p>Heists are episodic in nature, so they thrive across genres. They are easily serialized. Heists thrive on suspense; as things go bad for group A, cut to group B.</p>
<p>JW: Any syndicated TV show will eventually heist and Rashomon. It is so fun to see stories not originally created to tell heist story, adapt to heist. See Widows (movie) - the wives of the heist crew that died; they have the plan; they will not die without trying; they wake up to who they would be if they didn’t let someone organize parts of their life.</p>
<p><em>JM: Why are crimes/heists so interesting?</em></p>
<p>JJ: It’s a way to strike back at an unjust society, and at the same time, winning for oneself.</p>
<p>NW: Normal people do it. If it were a group of superheros it wouldn’t be a heist, it would be a mission - they can just use their powers like a battering ram.</p>
<p>JW: Avengers Endgame is not a time heist, but a time shopping spree. Can I get the timestone? It’s not theft, it’s a cash advance.</p>
<p><em>Cons vs. heists</em></p>
<p>A heist is an infiltration of space; a con is an infiltration of trust. A con is often central to a heist but doesn’t need to be. A con by itself is harder to make work because we’re terrified of being manipulated or being seen as a manipulator; a con with a heist becomes forgivable.</p>
<p><em>Recommendations</em></p>
<ul>
<li>The Hot Rock (a Series of Unfortunate Events for thieves)</li>
<li>Widows (movie) - the wives of the heist crew that died; they have the plan; they will not die without trying; they wake up to who they would be if they didn’t let someone organize parts of their life.</li>
<li>Inception (movie)</li>
<li>Black Summer (movie) - zombie heist</li>
<li>Impostors (TV show) - exes of same woman band together, having all been scammed by her</li>
<li>Neuromancer, William Gibson</li>
<li>Quantum Thief, Hannu Rajaniemi</li>
<li>A closed and Common Orbit, Becky Chambers (AI navigates becoming human, after being a ship’s intelligence. The book builds up to a heist. It is quiet and loving with high emotional stakes.)</li>
<li>Steal the Sky, Meagan O’Keefe</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="marvelous-mundane-the-impossible-inadequate-40-minute-history-of-how-fiction-got-its-genres-sat.-2pm">Marvelous &amp; Mundane: The impossible, inadequate 40-minute history of how fiction got its genres (Sat. 2pm)</h3>
<p><strong>Speaker:</strong> Austin Grossman</p>
<p><strong>Description:</strong> Barriers between speculative and “literary” fiction are crumbling. In this talk, Austin Grossman tries and inevitably fails to understand how we got those barriers in the first place! It’ll be fast, fun, and messy.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.austingrossman.com/etc">Powerpoint</a></p>
<h3 id="how-we-write-this-is-how-you-lose-the-time-war-sat.-3pm">How we write “This is how you lose the time war” (Sat. 3pm)</h3>
<p><strong>Description:</strong> Max Gladstone and Amal El-Mohtar discuss how they co-wrote their epistolary spy vs. spy novella.</p>
<!-- This was a super-entertaining back-and-forth to listen to, and I can't do it justice here.-->
<p><em>Choosing the project</em></p>
<p>Amal and Max wanted a way to collaborate that allowed their complementary approaches to writing to reinforce rather than neutralize each other. An epistolary format naturally lended itself to this, because each could write all the letters for one character, and the story would be consistent. Max came up with the idea of a “time war,” because it could span a “huge range of causality and contexts,” and they could easily play in the world, as long as they followed simple ground rules.</p>
<p>M: A bad scenario would be if neither of us felt like we had authority to play around. That sense of authority is really important, for authors trying to do their best work.</p>
<p><em>On writing letters</em></p>
<p>Amal and Max wrote physical letters to each other, on beautiful paper with wax seals.</p>
<p>A: It’s amazing how much pleasure we can get from communication, when we are now saturated with it. Email takes away from writing a lot of the time.</p>
<p>M: Both of us have been overwhelmed with social media. Our letters are not going to feed a machine learning algorithm. We can destroy them by dropping in water. They are fragile and permanent, in a way nothing on computer feels.</p>
<p>A: Communicating on internet feels like knitting. It’s taking form, taking up space, but can unravel so easily because there’s no knot until the very end.</p>
<p><em>Collaboration</em></p>
<p>They wrote all of the story during their time together, mostly sitting across from each other in a gazebo, with their computers, writing at the same time. They discussed the situation, but never the letters, so it was always a surprise. Max wrote 4 times as fast at the beginning, but as the project went on Max slowed down and Amal sped up; they naturally synced so they finished at the same time. They wrote 3 out of 5 acts in 9 days at a retreat, and finished the rest when they met later.</p>
<p>A: It’s a positive feedback loop. You get the gratification of someone reading your work, and reading something addressed to you, immediately.</p>
<p>M: It’s like jamming in a band.</p>
<p>A: It has little to do with the skill you bring, and more with the generosity and capacity for listening and delighting in each other. It’s like fusion in Steven Universe.</p>
<p><em>Theory of time-traveling queers</em></p>
<p>A: On my theory about time traveling queers: A disproportionate number of time travel stories are coming out this year. I realized they were mostly written by queer woman, foregrounding them and romances, in a world with no homophobia:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/40523931-the-light-brigade">Light Brigade</a> <!-- Kameron Hurley--></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/41035725-the-psychology-of-time-travel">Psychology of time travel</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/39332603-alice-payne-arrives">Alice Payne Arrives</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/36187158-gods-monsters-and-the-lucky-peach?ac=1&amp;from_search=true">Gods, Monsters, and Lucky Peach</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/43263807-the-future-of-another-timeline?ac=1&amp;from_search=true">The future of another timeline</a></li>
</ul>
<p>I asked the authors when they wrote the stories, It was all in 2016. Everyone was talking about how we’re in the worst timeline: David Bowie died, the US election. Brexit happened when we were writing the novella.</p>
<p>They were all saturated with abusive, gaslighty environments. Time-travel had an escapist, resistance quality. Why the foregrounding? Marginalized people are always fighting a time war, fighting the erasure of our time narratives. You don’t need a time war to erase someone, you just need selective memory. When we recuperate lives from this blanketing whiteness like snow, we are literating changing history and the future.</p>
<!-- Poetry breaks language into meaning. As genre writers we break reality into truth. -->
<h3 id="interview-stephen-graham-jones-sat.-4pm">Interview: Stephen Graham Jones (Sat. 4pm)</h3>
<p><strong>Biography</strong>: Stephen Graham Jones is a Piikáni (Blackfeet) author of cutting-edge fiction, ranging from the crime, horror, and science fiction genres to the purely experimental. His work has been multiply nominated for the Shirley Jackson, Stoker, and World Fantasy Awards, with Mapping the Interior (2017) winning the Stoker Award for Superior Achievement in Long Fiction. He has also won the Texas Institute of Letters Award and been the recipient of a National Endowment of the Arts fellowship in fiction. Playful, inventive, sincere, imaginative, touching, and horrifying, Jones’s work spans genres and defies the cynicism and alienation of postmodern literature.</p>
<p><em>On writing</em></p>
<!--Q: You said that Demon Theory is 100% autobiography.-->
<p>S: [on Demon Theory being “100% autobiography”] Often the writing process is: write 10-12 pages quickly, hit a wall, cast about on social media, and repeat. When I wrote Demon Theory, there was no social media, so every time I hit a wall, I reached into my life and put my life in. It’s not being very creative.</p>
<p>S: I am someone with very low standards. There is no such thing as writer’s block. When you lower your standards you can get a lot of work done.</p>
<p>S: Janet Broa (?) gave me the best piece of writing advice. She said that her biggest regret was that while living with family, she would write in the study room with the door closed. I resolved to leave the door open, or write in the living room. Books are great, but family is everything.</p>
<!--S: I write for revenge, against teachers who singled me out.-->
<p><em>Starting out</em></p>
<p>S: I was always moving from school to school; one semester I had 83 truancies out of 83 school days. Other kids pushed me around to see if I would push back.</p>
<p>S: I never planned on going to college, just on being a farmer. When I was 19 years old, my mom told me, “You need to get out of town” and gave me a suitcase with enough money to go to 1 semester of school. I took a beginning philosophy course. Everyone had read the reading and talked about it as if it mattered; I had never been among people like this. So I took loans and jobs and worked my way through college.</p>
<p>Some police officers came into class one day because my uncle had been burned and I was the only family they could find. I got bored in the hospital so I wrote a story. I didn’t do the homework assignment and submitted the story instead; my teacher typed it and submitted it for a department award. That was my first check from writing.</p>
<p><em>Teaching</em></p>
<p>S: If I don’t give 100% on teaching, then I don’t give 100% on writing.</p>
<!-- writing for revenge - I write for revenge, against teachers who singled me out. -->
<!-- teaching: If I don't give 100% then I don't give 100% on writing -->
<p><em>Why horror?</em></p>
<p>S: People used my first novel, Demon Theory, as a lens to focus on American Indian culture, rather than reading it as a book. That’s a weird way to use art. So then I wrote zombies and slashers; what would they make of that?</p>
<p>S: When I was a kid, my aunt and uncle knocked on my door and asked whether they could sleep on the floor with me. They saw a Halloween movie and couldn’t sleep alone that night. I thought, what could push these people to sleep on the floor with me? Horror. I’ve been staring into the darkness ever since.</p>
<p><em>When were you most scared?</em></p>
<p>S: When I was 4 years old, my stepdad brought me to the edge of Kleechie Pit, 60 feet deep, gave me his beer, and dropped off the cliff. I thought he was gone until some time later he tapped me on the shoulder. It turned out that 12 feet down he had grabbed onto a ledge and walked to the side.</p>
<!--
## Interview: Tananarive Due (Sat. 5pm)

**Biography:** Tananarive Due is a teacher in the creative writing MFA program at Antioch University Los Angeles and has been inducted into Northwestern University’s Medill School of Journalism’s Hall of Achievement, but she is best known as an author of speculative fiction. She has won the New Voice in Literature Award, the Carl Brandon Society’s Kindred Award, the American Book Award, and the NAACP Image Award, and her short fiction has appeared in several best-of-the-year anthologies. With her husband, Steven Barnes, she writes the Tennyson Hardwick mystery series.

*On screenwriting vs. writing prose:* 
Screenwriters collaborate because it's such a big process, like construction. Writing prose is more like dreaming. It took me a long time to figure out how to engage joy in screenwriting, get past the treatment stage.

writerduet.com - googledoc for screenwriting.
-->
<!--DM with Jordan Peele. Twitter cuts out the middleman.-->
<!-- The Reformation, Boston Review
Trial Day-->
<h3 id="hospitable-worlds-sat.-7pm">Hospitable Worlds (Sat. 7pm)</h3>
<p>Just one thing:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Get in the hoverdog, nerds!”</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 id="how-much-science-is-enough-science-sat.-8pm">How much science is enough science? (Sat. 8pm)</h3>
<p><strong>Panelists:</strong> Marc Abrahams, David DeGraff, Anna Kashina, Kathy Kitts (Moderator), Vivian Shaw</p>
<p><strong>Description:</strong> Some topics require more scientific know-how than; others. How much do writers need to know for particular topics—and how do they know how much they need to know? What are some techniques for acquiring necessary knowledge without getting a PhD? This panel of scientist-writers offers helpful guidance.</p>
<!--
MA: Most readers are not like the ideal reader. Especially kids who have not been exposed to the science, and this is their first chance to know that it exists. Put enough information so they are hooked and no more.

DD: Star Trek is half the reason I became an astronomer?

What makes a story survive iffy science?

MA: A well-told story.

AK: Character.

VS: Internal consistency.

MA: Tom Swift books (motorboat/cycle, searchlight, electric rifle) Taser. Enough to be exciting.

DD: Larry Niven Mercury story

AK: Jurassic Park.

VS: Black matter (heist)-->
<p><strong>Highlights from Panel Discussion:</strong></p>
<p><em>Talking to scientists:</em></p>
<p>DD: Email scientists. They are usually happy to talk about their work. Especially those on twitter. (K: And especially grad students; they have time.)</p>
<p>MA: Scientists are clever. With questions you don’t know how to ask, you can ask “how could this work” and then shut up. They will work like crazy, find 1 million ways it might be done. Scientists are the best audience for that story.</p>
<p>KK: Find EPO (education and public outreach) programs. For all NASA grants, a certain percentage has to go towards EPO. They hire someone to be a spokesperson for each mission; reach out to the EPO director; they can help you formulate the question.</p>
<p><em>Recommendations:</em></p>
<ul>
<li>Michael Collins, Carrying the Fire &amp; Liftoff</li>
<li>Chris Hadfield’s YouTube videos on space</li>
</ul>
<!-- 
Recs: Michael Collins, Carrying the Fire, Liftoff
Hatfield, YouTube videos.
-->
<h3 id="talk-with-jeanne-cavelos-inside-the-odyssey-workshop-sun.-10am-2pm">Talk with Jeanne Cavelos, Inside the Odyssey Workshop (Sun. 10am, 2pm)</h3>
<p><a href="http://www.readercon.org/bios/cavelos.htm">Biography</a></p>
<p><strong>Description:</strong> Jeanne Cavelos describes Odyssey, an intensive six-week program for writers of fantasy, science fiction, and horror held each summer in Manchester, NH. Current students and graduates will add their own perspectives. The talk will cover the structure of the program, the work required, common struggles of writers, and the pros and cons of workshops.</p>
<!-- Jeanne Cavelos just came from the Odyssey writing workshop, where she had "2 hours" of sleep for the past 6 weeks. -->
<p><em>Q: How did you transition from astrophysicist to writer?</em></p>
<p>J: Pay attention to what you care about, what your passion is and how to follow it, instead of bowling ahead on the path you are on.</p>
<p>I am a thorough person (I write thorough critiques), but it is not always good to complete something.</p>
<p>I studied astrophysics in college; my goal was to be an astronaut. I worked at the astronaut training division at NASA and at home, on psychic western novel. I liked dreaming more. I finished a 811-page novel, realized it was horrible, and so got a MFA in creative writing.</p>
<p>I worked at Bantam Doubleday as an editorial assistant. As I made my way up the ladder, I took more work home at night. I read about an editor retiring, saying that they now finally had time to write. I knew I had to get out before that happened to me!</p>
<p>I moved to New Hampshire, and continued to work with writers through the Odyssey workshops; that was 24 years ago. Besides the workshops, we also have online classes (announced October, held January to February), professional critiquing services, podcasts, and online salons.</p>
<!--
Neverending for grads
online classes
prof critique service
free podcasts, online salon
-->
<p><em>On making a writing habit</em></p>
<p>J: Set hours for fiction writing, schedule it like a job. When you do everything else first, you are left over with no time for writing. Set a goal to do e.g., 1 hour every day, and do it at the same time. 95% of successful writers write in the morning. Write every day for 6 months and see how you feel. Give it a fair shot.</p>
<p>It’s about rewards: Some people pay themselves for time writing, like $10 each time they finish or submit a story, to spend on things they would never otherwise allow themselves to buy.</p>
<p><em>Clarion workshop structure</em></p>
<p>J: Class is 4.5 hours, 5 days a week. 3 hours a day is lecture and discussion; 1.5-2 hours is critiquing manuscripts. Most other workshops don’t spend a lot of time on lecturing and giving techniques. But lectures and critiques go hand-in-hand: if you get feedback that you need to improve ABC, and no one tells you how, it’s not going to help. The workshop changes the process by which you generate stories.</p>
<p>There is a thorough curriculum, including: making the protagonist struggle to achieve goal, plotting in acts (escalations), creating strong character, point of view, eliminating unintentional distance, telling and showing (how and when to do each), showing character emotions, identifying the best sentence structure for the idea, what each scene of story should do, publishing industry.</p>
<p>Every day there is a writing exercise, and 2 stories to critique. It takes 2-5 hours. Students also work on their own stuff, turning in a new submission each week, up to 6000 words.</p>
<p>I personally meet with each student at least 3 times over the course of the program. I give detailed feedback; my critiques are usually &gt;2000 words. I make a list of common strengths and weaknesses in their work. We talk about them, choose a weakness to attack, and make a plan.</p>
<p>As an editor, I’ve collected different methods that work for different writers, and offer many different possibilities. I see how your brain works; what are the steps you’re missing?</p>
<p>Clarion has less continuity, and teaching is divided between 6 writers, so topics are covered more unevenly; there is more focus on networking.</p>
<p>[On critique workshops] A lot of stuff can go wrong, you are handing you baby over to people; they are chopping it up with hatchets. It’s always at least a little painful; sometimes it’s a lot painful, depending on how much you have invested. You have to walk clear line, not be attacked or coddled, but told the truth. The rule is that it’s gotta be true… It doesn’t matter how someone else is doing. If they do bad, you aren’t a better writer. Focus on your own particular journey.</p>
<p>Everything needs to be true and helpful - specific. “This story sucks” may be the truth but doesn’t help, because it doesn’t offer the author any way to improve. (Remove the suckiness and Hugo award winner!) More specific feedback is “There is no suspense because nothing is at stake.” It can be tough, but it gives the author direction. Suggestions are important. Not because the author should take the suggestions, but because the author often doesn’t see any other possibilities; suggestions widen the possibilities. <!--World unbelievable because using microwave without electricity.--></p>
<!-- https://sff.onlinewritingworkshop.com/ -->
<!--Handout with questions before start writing - develop those underdeveloped.-->
<!--First, I ask what the student normally does. Bring idea to story level. State as sentence. An idea can spawn multiple stories - 1 million plots. -->
<p><em>More on writing</em></p>
<p>A common problem is that the protagonist doesn’t struggle to achieve a goal. Another is that the character or protagonist doesn’t fully come to life; often it’s because the circumstances don’t evoke emotion; there needs to be clear mental conflict.</p>
<p>Many writers don’t like outlining. Find a way to do it that’s useful. If you know the beginning and end, that’s an outline. Outlining is analytical, writing is instinctive. Think about character while outlining; have some “dreamtime” while outlining. Go back and forth between outlining and writing; brains are not assembly lines. The part of brain that read all those lectures on writing, is not the part of brain that does actual writing. Daily writing exercises help (for example, writing dialogue with strong beats).</p>
<!-- Clarion vs. Odyssey
I personally meet with each student at least 3 times over the course of the program. We talk about their strengths and weaknesses, choose one to attack, and make a plan. (Clarion has less continuity, divided between 6 writers.)
How do you plan for weaknesses?
Ex. Not have protagonist struggle to achieve a goal. First, I ask what they normally do. Bring idea to story level. State as sentence. An idea can spawn multiple stories - 1 million plots. 
Handout with questions before start writing - develop those underdeveloped.

Character/protagonist doesn't come to life. Writers have difficulty conveying emotion on the page. Often the circumstances don't evoke emotion. 

Many writers don't like outlining. Find a way to do it that's useful. If you know the beginning and end, that's an outline. 
Outlining is analytical, writing is instinctive. Think about character while outlining; have some "dreamtime" while outlining.
Go back and forth between outlining and writing; brains are not assembly lines.
Part of brain that read all those lectures on writing, is not part of brain that does actual writing. Need to connect those parts.
-->
<!-- Last day packing up - you have a lot of stuff in your car. I had to give up my apartment to come. I spent money on tuition, I have $20 and this is the best decision I've made in my life. Most extreme stories.-->
<!-- curriculum
Making the protagonist struggle to achieve goal
Plot in acts, escalations
Build and resolve protags
POV's
Elim unintentional distance
telling and showing, how and when to do each
show character emotions
identify best sentence structure for idea, not at random
what each scene of story should do
publishing industry (last week)
-->
<h3 id="graybeards-beyond-gandalf-sun.-11am">Graybeards beyond Gandalf (Sun. 11am)</h3>
<p><strong>Panelists:</strong> John Clute, Elizabeth Hand (moderator), Anna Kashina, Barbara Krasnoff</p>
<p><strong>Description:</strong> Relatively few stories have protagonists much older than the target audience, and the traits commonly associated with heroism aren’t often associated with age. Yet in speculative fiction there are all manner of ways to break the link between age and infirmity, or to defy or redefine the concept of aging. Panelists will explore the potential of elderly protagonists and unpack a hero’s journey that doesn’t get the attention it deserves.</p>
<p><strong>Highlights from Panel Discussion:</strong></p>
<p><em>Why is it challenging to write older characters (beyond wizard and sage characters)?</em></p>
<p>JC: Joseph Campbell’s “hero of a thousand faces” is a model we build stories on that is inherently biased against older protagonists. A story about a people who have only managed to survive, who hasn’t done too good a job of being grown up, doesn’t fix the pattern we expect.</p>
<p>EH: The hero’s journey is a model that is common in genre fiction, but not common in domestic fiction, where there are a lot more middle-aged character, like Mrs. Dalloway.</p>
<p>BK: Stories often stop when characters reach adulthood, get married, etc. Authors find it difficult to go beyond that.</p>
<p>EH: Culture in America is very centric despite differences in population. Baby boomers are advertised to be younger. We refuse to accept that we’re not getting younger.</p>
<p>(Someone commented that vampires are old characters who look young. Response: Immortal people have all the advantages of youth and old age (wealth and power). The problem is, most old people can’t look and act as if they are young.)</p>
<p><em>Recommendations:</em></p>
<ul>
<li>Terry Pratchett - Captain Grimes, Granny Weatherwax, three witches</li>
<li>Heinlein - <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lazarus_Long">Lazarus Long</a></li>
<li>Ursula Le Guin</li>
<li>Angela Carter <!--https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Angela_Carter--></li>
<li>Hope Mirrlees, <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/73574.Lud_in_the_Mist">Lud-in-the-Mist</a> - Nathaniel Chanticleer is a middle-aged, dull character who remains melancholy throughout. He is characterized wonderfully. He is different from his middle-aged friends, because he always hear the “note”, siren call of something different. As the story progresses, he fits in less than before. The book begins with a scene with him in the cemetery, and ends with his death.</li>
<li>Odyssey - Odysseus’s journey is a great model. It spans 20 years of him getting older. He is a wily man who manipulates and tells stories to the world. He tricks people and survives. He attempts not to return to his youth but to his heritage, to reclaim his rightful place.</li>
<li>Beowulf</li>
<li>Maria Dahvana Headley, A Mere Wife - feminist retelling of Beowulf</li>
<li>Cocoon (movie) <!-- 
https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/13827.This_Immortal
https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/1124895.Isle_of_the_Dead
--></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="making-first-contact-with-your-local-speculative-fiction-community-sun.-12pm">Making First Contact with Your Local Speculative Fiction Community (Sun. 12pm)</h3>
<p><strong>Panelists:</strong> Rob Cameron, Crystal M. Huff, Matthew Kressel, Jim LeMay, Lauren Roy</p>
<p><strong>Description:</strong> Readercon and other national conventions are great, but what’s happening in your backyard? Local cons, reading events, workshops, classes, and critique groups are just a few examples of places where you might find other speculative fiction fans. If those things don’t exist near you, it might be time to create them! Panelists will share their experiences with joining and building in-person fannish communities, including joys, perils, and practical advice.</p>
<p><strong>Highlights from Panel Discussion:</strong></p>
<p><em>Finding a critique group:</em></p>
<p>RC: The best way is to search <a href="http://www.meetup.com">meetup</a> in your city/state.</p>
<p>MK: What if you’re in a small city, and find nothing on meetup?</p>
<p>LR: You can find people who you are friends with online. I’m a big fan of online groups. I play on a RPG server, World of Warcraft. The forum has writing section, where people exchange stories. We had a small critique group going.</p>
<p>MK: There are people you can approach to ask. The best resource is the local library. You can go to the local college, and approach professors. I started a group in Hoboken New Jersey, by advertising with flyers on boards in coffeeshops.</p>
<p>CH: I’ve been setting up google hangouts with writing friends. Once a month for 2 hours, we check in and get to work. We bounce ideas, and pass each other googledocs. <!--Function - bounce ideas. Ready to be read. Pass googledoc between us. --> For the check-in, we talk about what’s going on emotionally, like if we’ve had an upsetting week, etc. What’s going on with my writing, where I am at? <!--Do you have thoughts? Back-and-forth on possibilities. We can see each other.--> <!--M: Great way to connect with writers not in local area. Chat for 5, write for 55. --></p>
<p>RC: If you just want critique, check out <a href="http://critters.org/">critters.org</a>. It’s a community where everyone is there to do same thing, an economy of stories, critique to be critiqued.</p>
<p>We (the Brooklyn Speculative Fiction Writers) have been experimenting with an online group - particularly for writers who have moved, or work night shifts and can’t make the normal times. We use google hangouts and google drive, and converse via hangouts, and workshop a maximum of 3 stories per meeting.</p>
<p>JL: I’m in Denver. Bookstores and coffeehouses are places to find out about writers’ groups. Bookstores in Denver often have well-known writers show up.</p>
<p>MK: Go to a local writing event in the community to meet writers, and people with similar interests. For example, <a href="https://www.kgbfantasticfiction.org/">Fantastic fiction at KGB</a>. For people who are introverted, being at reading allows you to just sit and absorb; there’s less pressure.</p>
<p>RC: Game stores are also good places.</p>
<p>MK: <a href="https://www.codexwriters.com/">Codex writers</a> has a straightforward application process; it’s a private forum of people who critique and give each other moral support. Subcommunities on reddit can also be supportive: /writing.</p>
<p>RC: I emailed an author, I love your work, and I’m writing with a story with an element similar to yours. That started a 2-month-long correspondence.</p>
<p>MK: SFWA has a <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1qdeX6QB_lxacHuqrq1I9uvTXZE1AYOGLT2Tdao83XAI/edit">mentoring program</a>.</p>
<h3 id="from-seed-to-story-how-to-escape-the-slush-pile-sun.-1pm">From Seed to Story: How to Escape the Slush Pile (Sun. 1pm)</h3>
<p><strong>Panelists:</strong> Martin Cahill, Scott Edelman, James Patrick Kelly (moderator), Benjamin C. Kinney, Kenneth Schneyer</p>
<p><strong>Description:</strong> As Ann Leckie explained in a 2013 blog post, even great writers will have stories rejected if they write 7,000 words around an underdeveloped idea. So what kind of research should go into a short story? How much plot and exposition are called for? What questions should the writer be asking and answering before they even start writing? Panelists will explore various methods by which a story seed can be nurtured into something publishable.</p>
<p><strong>Highlights from Panel Discussion:</strong></p>
<p>James Kelly started by asking how many rejection slips or letters the panelists had. Answers ranged from 400 to 2000. Kenneth Schneyer mentioned that one author got accepted to Asimov’s on their 79th submission.</p>
<p>Then they discussed the next story that they were going to write, and what they knew about it.</p>
<p>MC: When there’s a trope that I dislike, the way I figure out why is to write that story.</p>
<p>SE: I have an concept for a world, but the seed/concept is not the story. I need to know whose story it is and why it matters. Who would be changed in the most profound way? When I arrive at the answer, I know what it’s about. I’m going through possible genders, races, ages, etc. of the main character, and considering different possible plots.</p>
<!--J: Some fraction of my ideas come from dreams.-->
<p><em>What questions do you need to ask and answer before you start to write?</em></p>
<p>KS: Why would I or anyone else care about the story? I have a word file that’s the length of a short novel, with nothing but 1-3 sentence snippets of story ideas. The majority go nowhere.</p>
<p>SE: The comment that hurts me the most is “this is trivial.” Or “Why did you waste my time?”, “There is no sense of purpose,” “Does this matter?” So ask yourself: how many stories am I going to write in my lifetime, and do I want this to be one of those stories?<a href="#fn3" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref3"><sup>3</sup></a></p>
<p>MC: Who is changed or being challenged? What is the consequence of their actions?</p>
<p>BK: What makes it not trivial - what is the common human experience that it relates to?</p>
<p>JK: Why am I the person to write this story? Be cautious about writing to theme anthologies - too much constrained work can be deadening to the exploratory inner writer who wants to write new stuff and find themself.</p>
<p><em>JK: How do you know when you’ve done enough research and it’s time to start writing?</em></p>
<p>KS: Do enough to start writing, and then do the research you need. It’s so hard to get myself writing that I don’t want anything to stand in between. I write a first draft, and then research and correct.</p>
<p>MC: Do enough research to empower you, not to bog you down. Google quick questions. For something specific, people who know will know you don’t; do enough to cover your ass.</p>
<p>KS: Often some research can get the story going. I read something nifty, and think, “That is so cool.”</p>
<p>SE+JK: You can write about something you’re intrinsically interested in - then you’d naturally have done the research over the course of your life.</p>
<p>KS: Use the power of handwavyness.</p>
<p><em>JK: How do you find problems and fix them?</em></p>
<p>BK: Two things can kill an otherwise competent story: no driving conflict (it’s good to have conflict on page 1), and lack of character agency.</p>
<p>Bring the cool thing up to the front. Put the reveal in paragraph 1, and explore the implications for the rest of the story?</p>
<p>MC: Use a writer’s group/beta readers.</p>
<p>JK: There are 3 parts of a story: beginning, middle, and end. Look at your own story. How much of it is beginning, middle, and end?</p>
<p>The beginning ends when the main character walks through a one-way door, that they can no longer go back through. Similarly, the transition to the ending is irreversible.</p>
<p>KS: Find the core of the story. When I write the first draft, 80% of the time I don’t know what the story was about - what was compelling about it. Ask: where is my unconscious emotional energy? What is the thing that I felt was necessary to say? Don’t sell yourself short. You didn’t do it just because it was a fun idea/exercise. Somewhere there was something that made it urgent enough. Find what that is.</p>
<p>MC: As Cat Valente said, a short story is a series of investments, convincing the reader to keep reading.</p>
<p>Check out <a href="https://www.tor.com/2014/10/29/a-kiss-with-teeth-max-gladstone/">A Kiss with Teeth by Max Gladstone</a>. At cusp between the middle and the end, it seems to make a turn towards the really dark, but he flips the story on its head.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>I feel like this is how any professional community - of experts and aspirants - should be, and yet I’ve hardly found it anywhere else. Perhaps it’s because there are so many roads leading away from science fiction and fantasy that the people who are here really love it (it’s not a good way to get money; it’s not a good way to get conventional respect - it’s not as respected as literary fiction; for example, several people mentioned being nudged away from genre fiction in college and finding their way back). <!--I think the academic community has a lot to learn from this!--><a href="#fnref1">↩</a></p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>I find it much like “open questions” in an academic subject - what are interesting directions to pursue!<a href="#fnref2">↩</a></p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>See also <a href="https://holdenlee.wordpress.com/2014/02/18/kazuo-ishiguro-on-writing/">Kazuo Ishiguro on writing</a>.<a href="#fnref3">↩</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

  </div>

    

    <!-- Extension : Sharing buttons @ www.sharethis.com -->
    <span class='st_facebook_large' displayText='Facebook'></span>
    <span class='st_twitter_large' displayText='Tweet'></span>
    <span class='st_googleplus_large' displayText='Google +'></span>
    <span class='st_reddit_large' displayText='Reddit'></span>
    <span class='st__large' displayText=''></span>

    <div id="disqus_thread"></div>
    


  
    <script>!function(d,s,id){var js,fjs=d.getElementsByTagName(s)[0],p=/^http:/.test(d.location)?'http':'https';if(!d.getElementById(id)){js=d.createElement(s);js.id=id;js.src=p+'://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js';fjs.parentNode.insertBefore(js,fjs);}}(document, 'script', 'twitter-wjs');</script>
  </div>
  
</div>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Month of Writing, Part 0</title>
    <link href="http://holdenlee.github.io/blog/posts/writing/month_of_writing_part_0.html" />
    <id>http://holdenlee.github.io/blog/posts/writing/month_of_writing_part_0.html</id>
    <published>2019-06-11T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2019-06-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[
<div class="container">
  <div id="content">
    <div class="page header">
      <h1>Month of Writing, Part 0</h1>
    </div>
    
    <div class="info">
       <div class="subtitle"><p>Starting out</p></div> 
       
        <p>Posted: 2019-06-11 
          , Modified: 2019-06-11 
	</p>
      
       <p>Tags: <a href="/tags/writing.html">writing</a></p> 
    </div>
    
  </div>
  <!--/div-->

  

  <div class="blog-main">
    <p>I’m spending one month focusing on writing! If you want to stay updated on my work, you can request to join the <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/holden-readers">Holden’s Readers googlegroup</a>.</p>
<h2 id="where-i-am-now">Where I am now</h2>
<p>After five years of work, I finally received my Ph.D. in mathematics! During grad school, I’ve put aside my writing for extended periods of time. But no more; I’ve come to realize over the past few years how essential writing is for me. Some of the most blissful times I’ve had are when I’m writing; moreover, my writing ambitions are no less important to me than my academic ones.</p>
<p>I’m thankful to the communities of writers I have been part of over the past two years, who have helped me to realize this. I’m indebted to my friend who started <a href="https://archandarrow.princeton.edu/">Arch and Arrow</a>, a writing group at Princeton because she was “tired of writing alone in her room.” I’ve been inspired by the writing meetups I participated in during my summer in New York, which I wrote about <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1gBfuIygKNVX0Sx3o57cnzgejif76LpnxWjSkA70G3YM/edit">here</a>. It’s really made me see the value of having a community of like-minded people. If you are an aspiring writer I encourage you to check out a meetup in your area, or otherwise find some friends you can share writing with.</p>
<p>This spring I applied to three fiction workshops (Clarion, Clarion West, Odyssey). I was disappointed that I didn’t get in any of them, but the process of applying forced me to revise some of my stories, to reflect on my progress as a writer, and think about what my next steps are. So I’ve decided to take a month off from work to focus on my writing. I’ll mainly be working on stories, and also a few blog posts.</p>
<h2 id="goals">Goals</h2>
<p>My concrete goal is to write three short stories, and get them to a point where I feel good about sharing them with other people. I hope to do some revision, but it’s also OK to revise in the following weeks. I’ll focus on short stories because I can iterate much faster - I can learn from the previous one as I start the next one, and I can write stories that are different from each other to stretch my abilities. While I enjoy working on a novel more than a short story, I think the practice from writing more short stories will be more helpful at this time.</p>
<p>I want this month to not just be focused of finishing stories, but instead on being a writer more broadly:</p>
<ul>
<li>reading a lot of material</li>
<li>recording what I learn from reading</li>
<li>improve at particular aspects of the craft (through specific writing exercises and lessons)</li>
<li>generate and execute on a lot of ideas (I want to brainstorm lots of ideas and test-write some of them; this way I will have a lot of threads I could draw on later)</li>
<li>focus on making progress on a specific short stories/novella/novel</li>
<li>do research as necessary</li>
<li>becoming confident about being a writer (not feeling like an impostor)</li>
<li>becoming articulate about writing</li>
<li>engaging with other writers (ex. through exchanging and editing each other’s work)</li>
<li>sharing through email and blog</li>
<li>submitting stories for publication</li>
</ul>
<p>I want to expand the things I write about, and write what I <em>actually</em> want to write. There are some persistent themes in my writing (rational/optimization-minded people becoming disillusioned, or having the tables turned on them in terms of what’s important or valuable in life) that I would rather escape from. I was drawn to those themes as a response to the pressure from work, and they are not the bigger, more beautiful things I would write about if I were in a freer state of mind.</p>
<h2 id="the-bigger-picture">The bigger picture</h2>
<p>More than just putting in a lot of hours, I want to develop good reading and writing habits that will persist afterwards. For example, I want to “garden” my thoughts, develop thoughtful reactions to things I read, and be able to talk about them.</p>
<p>Even more broadly, I look forward to a month of self-reflection, discovery, and improvement. The practice of writing for me is more entangled with personal growth than math or computer science research is. My hope is that in freeing up the large amount of time that I would normally be working, that I can devote my full intellectual energy - rather than the dregs of the energy at the end of the day - to things that have fallen by the wayside.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for updates!</p>

  </div>

    

    <!-- Extension : Sharing buttons @ www.sharethis.com -->
    <span class='st_facebook_large' displayText='Facebook'></span>
    <span class='st_twitter_large' displayText='Tweet'></span>
    <span class='st_googleplus_large' displayText='Google +'></span>
    <span class='st_reddit_large' displayText='Reddit'></span>
    <span class='st__large' displayText=''></span>

    <div id="disqus_thread"></div>
    


  
    <script>!function(d,s,id){var js,fjs=d.getElementsByTagName(s)[0],p=/^http:/.test(d.location)?'http':'https';if(!d.getElementById(id)){js=d.createElement(s);js.id=id;js.src=p+'://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js';fjs.parentNode.insertBefore(js,fjs);}}(document, 'script', 'twitter-wjs');</script>
  </div>
  
</div>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>The Bookmaking Species, Ken Liu</title>
    <link href="http://holdenlee.github.io/blog/posts/talks/the_bookmaking_species.html" />
    <id>http://holdenlee.github.io/blog/posts/talks/the_bookmaking_species.html</id>
    <published>2018-08-15T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2018-08-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[
<div class="container">
  <div id="content">
    <div class="page header">
      <h1>The Bookmaking Species, Ken Liu</h1>
    </div>
    
    <div class="info">
       <div class="subtitle"><p>The evolution of books; how form shapes narrative</p></div> 
       
        <p>Posted: 2018-08-15 
          , Modified: 2016-08-15 
	</p>
      
       <p>Tags: <a href="/tags/books.html">books</a>, <a href="/tags/writing.html">writing</a>, <a href="/tags/story.html">story</a></p> 
    </div>
    
  </div>
  <!--/div-->

  <div class="toc"> <ul>
 <li><a href="#summary-and-takeaways">Summary and takeaways</a></li>
 <li><a href="#history-of-books">History of books</a><ul>
 <li><a href="#from-scroll-to-codex">From scroll to codex</a><ul>
 <li><a href="#the-west">The West</a></li>
 <li><a href="#east-asia">East Asia</a></li>
 </ul></li>
 </ul></li>
 <li><a href="#how-structure-influences-narrative">How structure influences narrative</a><ul>
 <li><a href="#webpages">Webpages</a></li>
 <li><a href="#aside---books-in-the-legal-profession">Aside - books in the legal profession</a></li>
 <li><a href="#e-books">E-books</a></li>
 </ul></li>
 <li><a href="#the-untapped-potential-of-electronic-reading-and-the-memex">The untapped potential of electronic reading, and the memex</a></li>
 <li><a href="#questions-and-answers">Questions and answers</a></li>
 </ul> </div>

  <div class="blog-main">
    <p>These notes are based on <a href="https://kenliu.name/">Ken Liu</a>’s lecture “The bookmaking species” at the Swiss Institute. I’ve loosely paraphrased and condensed his talks; any errors or misrepresentations are due to me.</p>
<h2 id="summary-and-takeaways">Summary and takeaways</h2>
<ul>
<li>There’s a fascinating history behind the shift from scrolls to codices (the bound book format we are familiar with) that happened in both the West and East; it’s influenced by both technological and cultural/religious factors.</li>
<li>The structure of a book, as well as economic, historical, and cultural factors of the times, shapes the stories that gets told. The types of stories evolve - for example, TV shows nowadays have more complex plots than ever before.</li>
<li>The potential of electronic books for new types of storytelling, and better ways of recording and interacting with knowledge, has been largely untapped. Instead, e-books have mostly been formatted to imitate traditional books. As it is now, the Internet is a pale imitation of Vannevar Bush’s vision of the memex augmenting human intelligence.</li>
<li>Storytellers (writers, film producers, etc.) like to think that their profession is one of the most immune to the machine learning/AI revolution. However, machine learning is already playing a part in helping artists cater to what the public desires, and its role will only increase in the future.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="history-of-books">History of books</h2>
<p>I’m interested in books as artifacts, the history of books, and how the type of book changes the story that is told.</p>
<p>(One cool book is <a href="http://visual-editions.com/tree-of-codes">Tree of Codes</a> by Jonathan Foer, which creates a new book by cutting out pieces from an old book.)</p>
<p>What is a book? The familiar bound and paginated book is only one type of book, known as the <strong>codex</strong>. Before that was the <strong>scroll</strong>. Books can come in many forms: the earliest were oracle bones, with characters written for divination; other forms are cuneiform, papyrus, bamboo strips, and Incan <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quipu">quipus</a>. Now we have e-books. (I used them long before they were popular. The <a href="https://wiki.mobileread.com/wiki/Rocket_eBook">rocket e-book</a> was the earliest model. To download a good-sized book you had to plug in a phone cable and wait ten minutes).</p>
<p>The scroll came before the codex, and for a long time was the only format, or the more prestigious format. Scrolls were considered more intellectual - for instance, diplomas were depicted as scrolls.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dead_Sea_Scrolls">Dead Sea Scrolls</a> had aspects of the codex: the text was divided into pagelike columns, and so it could be folded concertina-style.</p>
<p>Legend has it (probably apocryphal) that Julius Caesar was the first to fold scrolls because he wanted to take books with him during the first Gaelic War.</p>
<h3 id="from-scroll-to-codex">From scroll to codex</h3>
<p>How did the codex overtake the scroll? There are two main reasons, technological and cultural/religious, and a similar story played out in both the western and eastern world.</p>
<h4 id="the-west">The West</h4>
<p><strong>Technological:</strong> It wasn’t until 200-300 AD that the codex became dominant. It’s no accident that this coincided with Christianity becoming the state religion, and the dominant religion, in the Mediterranean.</p>
<p>The codex had enormous advantage over the scroll as a medium for Christians to spread their teachings. A codex is a random access medium: you can instantly flip to any page. A codex allows innovations such as page numbers, indices, and tables of contents. Codices are easier to copy and produce. They are compact and portable, utilizing both sides of each page.</p>
<p><strong>Cultural:</strong> But this is not the whole story. Codices existed before they became popular; why didn’t they become the standard given their obvious benefits?</p>
<p>The earliest codices were formed from bundles of letters - people saved letters from loved ones who lived far away, and bound them together. Thus codices had a mundane association to them: they were not prestigious, nor philosophical, like scrolls; they were like paperback is to hardcover today.</p>
<p>The Christian scriptures, however, were in the form of letters, so it was natural to follow the tradition of binding them into a codex. In addition, Christians wanted to distinguish themselves from Jews, whose holy book, the Torah, is the quintessential scroll.</p>
<h4 id="east-asia">East Asia</h4>
<p>The word for volume, 冊 is in the shape of two strips of bamboo bound together.</p>
<p>As in the West, scrolls were the prestige format, seen as ancient and powerful (and still are - people do calligraphy on scrolls, not in codices). Paintings were done on scrolls. (In museums they are laid completely flat, to be viewed as static, unscrolled objects, but this is not how they were originally seen. They were unrolled so that viewers saw a window at a time.)</p>
<p>The codex was invented in China in the 7th century AD.</p>
<p><strong>Technological:</strong> The codex rose to prominence in the Tang dynasty, the era of classical poetry. Back then, composing poems was the way to show you were smart (like op-ed medium think pieces nowadays). You hoped that your poem would go viral, and be heard by government officials.</p>
<p>To compose poems, people needed rhyming dictionaries, and codices are undoubtedly the right form for dictionaries. (Imagine trying to use a rhyming dictionary in a scroll format!)</p>
<p><strong>Cultural/religious:</strong> One of the largest scale mass translations in ancient times was that of Buddhist texts from India into Chinese. The texts were written on palm leaves and bound using strings. As they were holy books, people wanted to preserve the format as closely as possible. China didn’t have palm leaves, but had plenty of paper - the Chinese analogue of palm leaves - so they made the texts into paper connected via string. The Chinese word for page was the same as the Chinese word for leaf (葉) until it got changed to 頁 in Republican times.</p>
<h2 id="how-structure-influences-narrative">How structure influences narrative</h2>
<p>A book is not merely the abstract set of words that is contains. The book as physical artifact influences the story that it tells. The modern novel is 350 pages long because 350 pages is a standard book size. Epic fantasies come in trilogies not for the reasons that authors come up with afterwards (the first book is the thesis, the second the antithesis, the third the synthesis) but because this is what publishers think what readers that. This trend originated with Lord of the Rings, which ironically was written as one long book and only split into three books because it was too large.</p>
<p>E-books have given rise to lengths that were not popular before: both shorter novels (~40,000 words) which were not viable in the familiar format, and larger novels (600,000 to 1 million words) which can’t be bound into traditional books. There is no narratological reason that books have to be a certain length.</p>
<p>The Chinese e-book market is dominated by very long serial novels. There is intense competitions between authors. They gain readers by posting serial installments for free, and have to write 2000 characters every day - often including holidays - to be competitive. (Dickens also wrote in serial installments; when he took a week off he got death threats.) The most successful stories become TV dramas and are turned into print editions (though they are so long I don’t know who would buy them).</p>
<p>Modern storytelling has changed because of Game of Thrones. TV shows (e.g. Friends) used to be made up of episodes which could stand on their own, so one could jump in anytime. Ever since Game of Thrones, however, we have wanted long, complex stories that last the whole season and that we can watch in binges. <!-- soap opera--> We are in a unique age which has the most complicated narrative stories that humankind has ever written. There is no way to follow Lost without wikis, and even George R.R. Martin says that he relies on fan wikis.</p>
<h3 id="webpages">Webpages</h3>
<p>The scroll has returned in the digital age, as the format for websites. People get mad if a website is broken up into pages - is the website just trying to increase ad views?</p>
<p>Early on, people figured out how to modify the CSS to get infinite scroll; it was the cool thing to do on tumblr.</p>
<p>However, history was not so certain. There are two models for hypertext, the scroll model and the card model. The card model has breaks the text into smaller chunks with links between them. One reason the scroll model won is that it has all the benefits of the scroll and the codex: with anchors and links, clickable table of contents, and indices produced by search.</p>
<p>Ironically, however, although the scroll has cultural significance as an authoritative relic, it is the written page that has hold on us now - as something more romantic than electronic text.</p>
<h3 id="aside---books-in-the-legal-profession">Aside - books in the legal profession</h3>
<p>As a lawyer, one of my angsts against the legal profession is its formal (“blue book”) citation method. It’s a system tied to hardcover books. Walk into a lawyer’s office and you’ll see bookshelves, one on either side, like a repository of arcane wizarding knowledge.</p>
<p>It’s a stage prop. I’ve consulted the books about twice in my career.</p>
<p>Instead, lawyers use legal databases to find information. In the databases, the text is in the form of an infinite scroll, but with ugly symbols denoting the page numbers, etc. It persists as a fiction that lawyers are consulting paper; the physical books are authoritative even though nobody has been using them for decades.</p>
<h3 id="e-books">E-books</h3>
<p>Kindle books are imitating the codex - for example in the ability to have page numbers (useful for citing). Apple is the worst offender, it has a “bookshelf” and when you flip the page there is an animation like an actual page flipping.</p>
<p>Codices aren’t any good when they only imitate scrolls. Likewise e-books aren’t any good if they just imitate paper books.</p>
<p>The New Yorker app reimagines what a electronic magazine can look like. It has articles side by side, and each article is an infinite scroll; it effectively utilizes a 2-D grid.</p>
<p>There’s great potential for hypertext fiction. We haven’t reimagined navigation yet.</p>
<h2 id="the-untapped-potential-of-electronic-reading-and-the-memex">The untapped potential of electronic reading, and the memex</h2>
<p>Vannevar Bush, in his essay <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/1945/07/as-we-may-think/303881/">As we may think</a>, envisioned the <em>memex</em>, a most wondrous device for electronic reading. It’s commonly described as the predecessor of the Internet, but I disagree: it’s far more impressive.</p>
<p>Machines have helped us amplify our physical capabilities, but they have been much more limited in amplifying our mental capabilities. One difficulty is that how we think is different from how computers think: humans are association machines, thinking in metaphors and accessing thoughts in a random fashion. Why not use computers to enhance this style of thinking? In Vannevar Bush’s vision, a memex features two screens to display text, and a user can tap to make a connection between them. He imagines that the primary work of the reader is to make these kinds of rich semantic links. The resulting database of links becomes a external manifestation of the reader’s mind.</p>
<p>It is much easier for us to recall something by following associations than by looking up a random word. For example, how many times have you thought: I wish I could recall that website - I saw it after this and before that, and it reminds me of this, but I can’t remember the words I used to find it…</p>
<p>Interested (and interesting) explorers of the universe and of human learning will forge trails of associations through all knowledge. A person could jump from the Origin of Species to Darwin’s original papers, to finches, to customs of the natives, to British politics, and so forth, to construct a natural history of a subject within the archive of human learning. The resulting rich web of links can be published as a book of its own, so that readers can follow it and build their own web on top of it, to create meta-associations. This will make learning much more personal and guided in a way we don’t really comprehend. The closest thing that we have now is browsing Wikipedia. Imagine if all learning were a richer form of Wikipedia where you could lose yourself in association. Authors could become known for the originality and beauty of their association webs. <!--(You would build on top of that.)--> <!--That's the true vision of the memex, and --> You would build on top of them like a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Commonplace_book">commonplace book</a>, except that it’s a commonplace web. The Web is a poor and pale imitation of this future!</p>
<p>As technology changes the kinds of books that are possible, the stories we can tell also change, and that’s a wonderful thing. I don’t believe we should be stuck with the scroll or codex. I can’t wait to see how electronic reading will develop as we push forward. I don’t lament the death of the paper book; what will come to replace it will be far more interesting.</p>
<h2 id="questions-and-answers">Questions and answers</h2>
<p><strong>Q:</strong> A lot of bookstores are having trouble. What’s the future for bookstores?</p>
<p><strong>A:</strong> Bookstores aren’t going away, though chains have been hit hard. But they cannot compete with indie bookstores, which are community centers with author events; their curatorial role will not go away. Individual readers do wish to participate in the events and support the bookstore. The general trend is that content is digitized and turned into advertising for things can’t be easily copied.</p>
<p>A similar thing has happened in the music industry. Here, the thing that can’t be easily copied is performance. Authors have not quite figured out what “performance” is for them. (It’s incredibly boring to watch an author write a book.) Musicians thought digitization was the end of the world, but now there is now more music than ever before, and many musicians are living better than ever, though music is being sold for cheaper. It’s not true for everyone though - musicians who don’t rely on live performances don’t do as well - it does threaten certain business models.</p>
<p><strong>Q:</strong> What are some books that push these new frontiers?</p>
<p><strong>A:</strong> I haven’t seen them so much in books as in games: visual novels (essentially books with programming around them) are pushing narrative in new interesting directions.</p>
<p>I’d like to see more experimentation. Some publishers are doing interesting things, like <a href="https://www.serialbox.com/">serialbox</a>, who treats creating a serial story like creating a TV show, with writer’s rooms and seasons of stories. It’s an interesting model for book-writing.</p>
<p><strong>Q:</strong> Have you taken this into account in the format of your own books?</p>
<p><strong>A:</strong> I always envision them as physical books, with a map at the front, so that the reader can flip to it as they are reading. However, in the e-book it’s hard to refer to the map. Ironically, I had been blind to this. I’ve made the map available for download, and encouraged readers to print it out.</p>
<p><strong>Q:</strong> How is writing versus translating?</p>
<p><strong>A:</strong> It’s like the difference between composing and performing music, writing a play and acting. You use similar knowledge to do different things.</p>
<p><strong>Q:</strong> What is your approach to writing?</p>
<p><strong>A:</strong> I do unusual things, collaborating with ballet troupes, with the Guggenheim, doing art based on alternate reality. I like to experiment. I wrote a story that progressively loses words, so that you come to a different conclusion about what it’s about in the later versions.</p>
<p>For this exhibition, I was approached by someone who wanted to use the physical artifact of books to illustrate an abstract concept. I was hired at my attorney rate to curate a book collection on what comes to mind when I think about the law in China. There’s a temptation to be political, but I have an aversion to that. There is nothing wrong with art as resistance, but it has to be open to interpretation.</p>
<!--10141-->
<p>Making art is like building a house. Certain houses are narrow and confining; unless the reader contorts themselves they don’t feel comfortable… But if the house has open spaces, allows you to walk around, then the reader is comfortable moving in it, exploring and discovering and making the house their own.</p>
<p>I like the second approach better, because I’m a deep believer in the reader response theory of literature. Art takes two people to create the work. The reader is never a passive participant, but an active meaning maker.</p>
<p>Before the text can be unpacked, it has to be packed with the reader’s assumptions and interpretive frameworks.</p>
<p><strong>Q:</strong> If the future is a manifestation of (seemingly) random associations, would that require an evolution of narrative itself?</p>
<p>Media theorists have studied and debated this forever. There’s always the argument that the long-form story has an important role in the way we think. This goes back to the days of Plato.</p>
<p>This argument over whether e-reading is rotting our brains is not a new argument. Plato railed against the techology of writing: it will rot our children’s minds, and won’t know how to conduct rhetoric, argue against the writers, tell truth from fiction.</p>
<p>As association-rich, interruption-rich reading becomes the norm, it will lead to a evolution in the way we judge and think about texts.</p>
<p>One of the most popular new forms of fiction right now is twitter/text fiction: stories told as a chain of fictional text messages. As an art form, this is very difficult to do, and I’ve been amazed at the results. We can have alternate reality games, challenging what narrative can do.</p>
<p>We’ll have to rethink narrative theories, but we’ve done this before. We thought <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Classical_unities">Aristotelian unities</a> were sacred, but movies, as a time random-access medium, have broken that apart.</p>
<!--so many different possib for narr 
will tech design drive narrative, -->
<p><strong>Q:</strong> How does technology influence narrative? Will the designers of technologies, creators of platforms determine what narratives are told? Or will the narratives people create push for technology to accommodate them?</p>
<p><strong>A:</strong> The future of art is going to be much more AI and audience-driven than we acknowledge. It’s mindblowing the way that AI has changed the way content is produced and consumed. For example, a lot of music in films is created by AI, but we don’t notice it. Even the way human creators create is shaped by AI: in a lot of visual art manipulation, the algorithms do a lot of the work and the human simply acts as a judge.</p>
<p>The story of Netflix shows that dramatic art is no exception. No one thought it would succeed as a studio because it was supposedly just a platform to distribute content. However, in seven years it has gone from nothing to a top studio, with some of the most popular shows on earth. It’s now considered great prestige if you as a showrunner can get a show with Netflix.</p>
<p>Their success has been possible because they are very data-driven. For example, their decision to pick up House of Cards was data-driven. They discovered that there would be a critical mass of people who are fans of Kevin Spacey, people who love David Fisher’s work, and who loved the original BBC series. They’ve learned that people don’t get hooked from the pilots, but only after 2-4 episodes. The platform is an unprecedented <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Panopticon">panopticon</a>: they track when you pause or skip a video, wait two days before watching the next one, can infer when you lose interest or find a series worth following. Never before has anyone been able to observe an audience at that level. They can use all this data to help produce popular shows.</p>
<p>An extreme example of data-driven content creation is pornography on demand. The industry keeps track of search queries and uses them to meet people’s demands. Pornography has embraced a data-driven approach because it is a limited format where the creative choices are small.</p>
<p>Data-driven authorship is a critical issue. A lot of artists have to be data-driven or be outcompeted by people who are.</p>
<p>Imagine a future where stories can adapt to individual readers based on what they want: if a reader wants a couple to be together, they will be; if they want a character to go away, then the character dies on the next page. Perhaps this is how people prefer their stories.</p>
<p>We treasure a Promethean vision of an artist, creating a masterpiece unsullied by what the public wants. However, there is a competing, utilitarian vision of the artist, enshrined in the constitution, as someone who fulfills a public need. Indeed, mass film and TV have been largely driven by a need to fulfill public desires. The difference is that it is now data-driven. This sounds dystopian, but it’s not a bad thing - many great TV shows have come out of this, and wouldn’t exist without it.</p>
<p>We’ll have to wait to see how this evolves. I like to think of AI as augmenting the creator, versus taking my job away, but maybe this is just wishful thinking.</p>
<!--
# Thoughts

Any tools like the memex? 
-->

  </div>

    

    <!-- Extension : Sharing buttons @ www.sharethis.com -->
    <span class='st_facebook_large' displayText='Facebook'></span>
    <span class='st_twitter_large' displayText='Tweet'></span>
    <span class='st_googleplus_large' displayText='Google +'></span>
    <span class='st_reddit_large' displayText='Reddit'></span>
    <span class='st__large' displayText=''></span>

    <div id="disqus_thread"></div>
    


  
    <script>!function(d,s,id){var js,fjs=d.getElementsByTagName(s)[0],p=/^http:/.test(d.location)?'http':'https';if(!d.getElementById(id)){js=d.createElement(s);js.id=id;js.src=p+'://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js';fjs.parentNode.insertBefore(js,fjs);}}(document, 'script', 'twitter-wjs');</script>
  </div>
  
</div>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>NIPS 2017 Deep learning panel</title>
    <link href="http://holdenlee.github.io/blog/posts/cs/ml/nips_2017.html" />
    <id>http://holdenlee.github.io/blog/posts/cs/ml/nips_2017.html</id>
    <published>2017-12-22T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-12-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[
<div class="container">
  <div id="content">
    <div class="page header">
      <h1>NIPS 2017 Deep learning panel</h1>
    </div>
    
    <div class="info">
       <div class="subtitle"><p>Summary</p></div> 
       
        <p>Posted: 2017-12-22 
          , Modified: 2017-12-22 
	</p>
      
       <p>Tags: <a href="/tags/neural%20network.html">neural network</a>, <a href="/tags/deep%20learning.html">deep learning</a>, <a href="/tags/machine%20learning.html">machine learning</a></p> 
    </div>
    
  </div>
  <!--/div-->

  <div class="toc"> <ul>
 <li><a href="#sa-name-one-aspect-of-dl-where-you-think-theory-can-make-a-deep-impact.">SA: Name one aspect of DL where you think theory can make a deep impact.</a></li>
 <li><a href="#sa-is-the-presence-of-adversarial-examples-simply-a-puzzle-or-is-it-a-fundamental-problem-which-will-give-deep-insight">SA: Is the presence of adversarial examples simply a puzzle, or is it a fundamental problem which will give deep insight?</a></li>
 <li><a href="#sa-is-generative-models-the-correct-approach-to-unsupervised-learning">SA: Is generative models the correct approach to unsupervised learning?</a></li>
 <li><a href="#sa-does-rl-need-deep-learning-other-than-to-sense-the-environment">SA: Does RL need deep learning other than to sense the environment?</a></li>
 <li><a href="#sa-generalization---is-it-just-a-puzzle-or-does-it-lead-to-fundamental-new-insights">SA: Generalization - is it just a puzzle or does it lead to fundamental new insights?</a></li>
 <li><a href="#a-do-we-need-to-go-beyond-first-order-methods">A: Do we need to go beyond first order methods?</a></li>
 <li><a href="#a-can-we-use-generative-models-to-prevent-adversarial-examples">A: Can we use generative models to prevent adversarial examples?</a></li>
 <li><a href="#sa-what-about-logic">SA: What about logic?</a></li>
 </ul> </div>

  <div class="blog-main">
    <p>This is a summary of the panel discussion at the NIPS 2017 <a href="https://ludwigschmidt.github.io/nips17-dl-workshop-website/">deep learning (bridging theory and practice) workshop</a>.</p>
<p>I’ve paraphrased the conversation; any misrepresentations are due to me.</p>
<p>Host: Sanjeev Arora (SA)</p>
<p>Panelists:</p>
<ul>
<li>Ruslan Salakhutdinov (RS)</li>
<li>Percy Liang (PL)</li>
<li>Yoshua Bengio (YB)</li>
<li>Peter Bartlett (PB)</li>
<li>Sham Kakade (SK)</li>
</ul>
<p>Audience (A)</p>
<h2 id="sa-name-one-aspect-of-dl-where-you-think-theory-can-make-a-deep-impact.">SA: Name one aspect of DL where you think theory can make a deep impact.</h2>
<p>SK: Model-based solution concepts.</p>
<p>PL: Inductive bias. This is important in language understanding. Right now, model creators are mostly guided by intuition. Attention mechanisms are an example of inductive bias.</p>
<p>PB: Optimization and statistical properties, and generalization. Even though models are hugely overparametrized, the optimization leads to a solution that generalizes.</p>
<p>YB: In the past, neural networks have been in the realm of theory. But now, people doing theory should look in many other places as well. For example, to figure out how to formalize questions about uniqueness of representations, we can investigate when we get unique solutions to nonlinear ICA.</p>
<h2 id="sa-is-the-presence-of-adversarial-examples-simply-a-puzzle-or-is-it-a-fundamental-problem-which-will-give-deep-insight">SA: Is the presence of adversarial examples simply a puzzle, or is it a fundamental problem which will give deep insight?</h2>
<p>SK: This is important in reinforcement learning (RL) because in some sense errors in RL always look like worst-case errors. Making progress on robustness in RL will be like making progress on adversarial learning. We don’t understand how error in RL compounds.</p>
<p>PL: When I first learned about adversarial examples I thought it was cute, but over the years I found that it led to many other ideas. It relates to interpretability, teaching, generalizing models to new distributions, robustness (is it learning the right model?), and having the right inductive bias. Adversarial examples good way to stress-test a model.</p>
<p>PB: Defending against adversarial attacks is important. Though, adversarial examples may be a phenomena of many systems (even humans).</p>
<p>YB: It’s not specific to neural nets, but a broader problem. My intuition from the beginning is that it has a lot to do with the fact that humans use a lot of extra information about the data distribution <span class="math inline"><em>p</em>(<em>x</em>)</span>, and this influences our classifiers in a strong way - we mostly learn <span class="math inline"><em>p</em>(<em>x</em>, <em>y</em>)</span>, not <span class="math inline"><em>p</em>(<em>y</em>|<em>x</em>)</span>. Attempts to jointly learn the input probability distribution and the classifier were not very convincing, so this early idea was forgotten.</p>
<p>RS: Building good generative models would help. But they are hard to build.</p>
<p>YB: If we capture 3-D models of images, a small perturbation won’t disturb them.</p>
<p>PL: Wouldn’t they? You can still attack the generative model.</p>
<h2 id="sa-is-generative-models-the-correct-approach-to-unsupervised-learning">SA: Is generative models the correct approach to unsupervised learning?</h2>
<p>SK: Even if density estimation can do extremely well, what we care about is the last bit of error. The generative model can be accurate in most natural senses, yet the model can still fail to get fill-in-the-blank questions like “Jane is going to work. Her car broke down. She was _ (late).” wrong most of the time. It won’t do well until it completely learns the distribution.</p>
<p>PL: How do we set up the objective functions to explain the high-level information and semantics?</p>
<p>PB: A central issue is, what’s the appropriate objective function? We can use user interaction to pin it down.</p>
<p>YB: Consider: if an algorithm models acoustics with an information-theoretical objective, it has hard time model speech, because that is only a few bits of relevant abstract information out of thousand bits of signal. Instead of considering the problem as a generative problem (with objectives like reconstruction error, entropy), look instead in the representation space: which directions matter? (See <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1709.08568">consciousness prior</a>.)</p>
<p>RS: I believe in generative models that try to learn about environment by interacting with it.</p>
<p>YB: Don’t predict in pixel space - predict in the abstract space.</p>
<p>SK: I believe in generative models for language. there, but we’re still missing concepts.</p>
<p>RS: 7-8 years ago, people thought dealing with pixels is a disaster, so they made features using HOG and SIFT. But deep nets work directly on pixels! The input is pixels, but deep nets go from that to a higher-level space.</p>
<p>PL: Learning to generate text isn’t the same as coming up with a generative model for text. We don’t to cover the space; RL can just go to a mode.</p>
<h2 id="sa-does-rl-need-deep-learning-other-than-to-sense-the-environment">SA: Does RL need deep learning other than to sense the environment?</h2>
<p>SK: In the vanilla control setting, I’m not convinced it does. For harder questions, I’m still not convinced current methods are doing anything more that just building a bridge between ways to represent the environment, and sequential decision-making solution. Harder questions involve logic and planning - is there currently an impressive demo where we’re seeing that? I think the deep learning part is just giving better representations of the environment.</p>
<p>PL: In the long term, RL will need sensing, the ability to hold large memory about the world, do reasoning, and express a complicated control policy.</p>
<p>PB: It would be surprising if you could solve complex control problems aside from sensing without having rich nonparametric classes - if there are not additional barriers. In most current examples you can get by with linear systems.</p>
<p>RS: Deep learning is helpful here because it learns the right representation for the task; it goes from the raw sensing to the representation and the policy, and you can just backprop. There are more things we can do beyond extracting features: have separate architecture for storing information, attention, etc.</p>
<p>PL: We need to have baselines. There are cases (in dialog and in control) where simple nondeep models with the right inductive bias do better than everything with a deep neural net. We need to carefully measure where the value of deep learning is coming in.</p>
<h2 id="sa-generalization---is-it-just-a-puzzle-or-does-it-lead-to-fundamental-new-insights">SA: Generalization - is it just a puzzle or does it lead to fundamental new insights?</h2>
<p>On a practical level, we can just hold out some data for testing.</p>
<p>PB: There is more to understand. Most interesting is the connection between optimization and generalization. At the qualitative level, we understand a lot of measures of complexity. What are the implications for regularization? Why is SGD effective in finding solutions that generalize well? When we get that insight, we will find better algorithms, in particular for very noisy cases.</p>
<p>PL: With a practitioner’s hat, I ask: if I understand the generalization/optimization story how would that change my behavior? I care about choosing families of functions with good inductive biases (that will make me have low approximation error) - this guides the first thing I do when I’m going into a new domain, and figuring out what works. Is there a more end-to-end way of understanding approximation of functions and generalization at same time, something that allows jointly optimizing them?</p>
<p>RS: It’s hard to beat the bag of tricks (SGD + dropout + batch normalization + momentum).</p>
<p>SK: The question is a proxy for thinking about algorithms which generalize. If all we care about is verification, just hold out data. We hope that the theory of generalization can help. On a fixed problem hard to beat SGD with dropout.</p>
<p>But there’s a richer set of questions from thinking about generalization more broadly: generalization between problems (transfer learning) multitask learning, domain adaptation - all frustrations of ML.</p>
<p>PL: If you train on sequences of length 5, can you generalize to length 10? Images of different size? Extrapolation is important, and necessitates learning the right concepts.</p>
<p>MR: Does a neural net learn sensible abstractions and high-level concepts? A cognitive neuroscience perspective may help. How do we rethink architecture (e.g. Jeff Hinton’s capsules)?</p>
<p>RS: Design new architectures with notions of invariance - this adds in prior knowledge. A CNN learns things that a non-convolutional net finds hard; a CNN has lots of prior knowledge!</p>
<p>Given a face with 3 eyes, a neural network still thinks it’s face. How do we incorporate priors? Memory is exciting (e.g., NTMs can write and read). It’s not clear how well they will work. How to design new architectures with inductive biases?</p>
<p>PL: Inductive biases are important for improving sample efficiency. It’s more necessary to learn the right thing. For images, classifiers aren’t robust to changing the fourier spectrum of the images.</p>
<p>I feel pessimistic that an architecture can magically learn the right thing, and have concepts that generalize well. But in practice, we can get good performance and useful products.</p>
<h2 id="a-do-we-need-to-go-beyond-first-order-methods">A: Do we need to go beyond first order methods?</h2>
<p>SK: In RL, a lot of solution concepts aren’t just first order. Many use trust region methods. How does Monte Carlo tree search fit in? There’s issues of discrete vs. continuous optimization</p>
<p>RS: It’s hard to beat SGD+momentum+BN. But there should be something going beyond it.</p>
<h2 id="a-can-we-use-generative-models-to-prevent-adversarial-examples">A: Can we use generative models to prevent adversarial examples?</h2>
<p>PL: Text adversarial examples cannot be detected by generative models. For adversarial examples, we need to think beyond the statistical worst case notion; <span class="math inline">$L^\iy$</span> is the tip of the iceberg.</p>
<p>SK: Theory has a valuable contribution to make, on robustness (to adversarial perturbation).</p>
<p>PL: Argmax is hard.</p>
<p>SA: There’s something off about an information theoretic approach to unsupervised learning. When I imagine a scene with people, it’s not clear that it’s coming out of a distribution.</p>
<p>PL: To generate language, if suffices to havea policy. Individual humans don’t have distribution over sentences. We all have different distributions, can still get high rewards.</p>
<p>SA: Is there a distribution?</p>
<p>PB: This is like the determinism vs. free will question… You generate sentences in particular way. There’s a distribution; I don’t see that as a problem.</p>
<p>SA: This could be a philosophical or a practical issue. On the practical side, the most important thing could be the last bit which is not learned.</p>
<p>PL: How do we fit language? Machine learning often learns generic responses, which not interesting. We could flip the KL, maximize expectation with respect to policy as opposed to the distribution. We don’t have to cover the space, just find one solution out of model, which is easier than modeling the whole distribution.</p>
<h2 id="sa-what-about-logic">SA: What about logic?</h2>
<p>SA: My favorite research problem is to combine differentiable techniques with what introspection tells us - old AI logic. Can we come up with differentiable reasoning?</p>
<p>RS: What about fuzzy logic?</p>
<p>PL: I work a lot on semantic parsing. Logic allows you to move big pieces of things. Taking the maximum works reliably. Get extrapolation for free.</p>
<p>On the other hand, logic is a straitjacket, and has sharp cliffs. <!--Given a trained neural net can we coerce it to logic?--></p>
<p>We can use logic by pragmatically encoding the primitives and having a good inductive bias; having a logical backbone is like growing a vine using trellises.</p>
<p>RS: How do we combine logical rules with deep learning, so that if the logical rules make sense then the model picks them up, and if not, it gets rid of them?</p>
<p>For David Silver’s work on Go, he noted that Go players had specific rules. The neural network discovered some of them, and kept the important ones.</p>
<p>We can put logical rules into the prior, but then the net should figure out what makes sense.</p>
<p>SK: In RL, planning seems logic-based. Alpha-go is a interesting example: it leans on MCTS heavily.</p>
<p>Here deep learning is fitting a continuous approximation of the world.</p>
<p>PL: I want to decouple the idea of logic as a representation vs. as a replacement for learning.</p>
<p>It’s more useful to think of it as a representation: certain parts of a problem have structure. Think of logic as making things digital vs. analog. For long-horizon situations, if you want to not forget, do error correction, and logic is doing something similar.</p>
<p>SA: Will there be grand synthesis of deep learning and 60’s/70’s (good-old-fashioned) AI?</p>

  </div>

    

    <!-- Extension : Sharing buttons @ www.sharethis.com -->
    <span class='st_facebook_large' displayText='Facebook'></span>
    <span class='st_twitter_large' displayText='Tweet'></span>
    <span class='st_googleplus_large' displayText='Google +'></span>
    <span class='st_reddit_large' displayText='Reddit'></span>
    <span class='st__large' displayText=''></span>

    <div id="disqus_thread"></div>
    


  
    <script>!function(d,s,id){var js,fjs=d.getElementsByTagName(s)[0],p=/^http:/.test(d.location)?'http':'https';if(!d.getElementById(id)){js=d.createElement(s);js.id=id;js.src=p+'://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js';fjs.parentNode.insertBefore(js,fjs);}}(document, 'script', 'twitter-wjs');</script>
  </div>
  
</div>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Crash Course in Complex Analysis</title>
    <link href="http://holdenlee.github.io/blog/posts/math/analysis/complex_cs.html" />
    <id>http://holdenlee.github.io/blog/posts/math/analysis/complex_cs.html</id>
    <published>2017-08-02T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-08-02T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[
<div class="container">
  <div id="content">
    <div class="page header">
      <h1>Crash Course in Complex Analysis</h1>
    </div>
    
    <div class="info">
       <div class="subtitle"><p>geared towards computer scientists</p></div> 
       
        <p>Posted: 2017-08-02 
          , Modified: 2017-08-02 
	</p>
      
       <p>Tags: <a href="/tags/complex%20analysis.html">complex analysis</a>, <a href="/tags/crash%20course.html">crash course</a>, <a href="/tags/numerical%20analysis.html">numerical analysis</a>, <a href="/tags/numerical%20integration.html">numerical integration</a>, <a href="/tags/polynomials.html">polynomials</a>, <a href="/tags/Chebyshev%20polynomials.html">Chebyshev polynomials</a></p> 
    </div>
    
  </div>
  <!--/div-->

  <div class="toc"></div>

  <div class="blog-main">
    <p>Here are notes for my talk “Crash course in complex analysis” for the Gems of TCS seminar.</p>
<ul>
<li>For a crash course, see the first chapter in my notes on analytic number theory, <a href="http://tiny.cc/annt" class="uri">http://tiny.cc/annt</a>. Proof sketches are in the <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/k2qf4oy754ln8og/complex_handwritten_notes.pdf?dl=0">handwritten notes</a>.</li>
<li>For applications, see notes <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/fn854rj0j98ij6d/complex_cs.pdf?dl=0">here</a>.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Abstract</strong>: Calculus on the complex numbers has an entirely different attitude from calculus on the reals. The additional structure of the complex numbers greatly enriches the theory of differentiable functions. I will cover (the many variants of) Cauchy’s Theorem, power (Laurent) series, and various inequalities (Hadamard three-lines and three-circles). I’ll give some applications including convergence rates for polynomial approximations and numerical integration, and a recent application to population recovery.</p>

  </div>

    

    <!-- Extension : Sharing buttons @ www.sharethis.com -->
    <span class='st_facebook_large' displayText='Facebook'></span>
    <span class='st_twitter_large' displayText='Tweet'></span>
    <span class='st_googleplus_large' displayText='Google +'></span>
    <span class='st_reddit_large' displayText='Reddit'></span>
    <span class='st__large' displayText=''></span>

    <div id="disqus_thread"></div>
    


  
    <script>!function(d,s,id){var js,fjs=d.getElementsByTagName(s)[0],p=/^http:/.test(d.location)?'http':'https';if(!d.getElementById(id)){js=d.createElement(s);js.id=id;js.src=p+'://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js';fjs.parentNode.insertBefore(js,fjs);}}(document, 'script', 'twitter-wjs');</script>
  </div>
  
</div>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>On the ability of neural nets to express distributions (at COLT 2017)</title>
    <link href="http://holdenlee.github.io/blog/posts/cs/ml/neural_net_distributions.html" />
    <id>http://holdenlee.github.io/blog/posts/cs/ml/neural_net_distributions.html</id>
    <published>2017-07-07T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[
<div class="container">
  <div id="content">
    <div class="page header">
      <h1>On the ability of neural nets to express distributions (at COLT 2017)</h1>
    </div>
    
    <div class="info">
       <div class="subtitle"><p>Holden Lee, Rong Ge, Tengyu Ma, Andrej Risteski, Sanjeev Arora</p></div> 
       
        <p>Posted: 2017-07-07 
          , Modified: 2017-07-07 
	</p>
      
       <p>Tags: <a href="/tags/machine%20learning.html">machine learning</a>, <a href="/tags/paper.html">paper</a>, <a href="/tags/neural%20network.html">neural network</a></p> 
    </div>
    
  </div>
  <!--/div-->

  <div class="toc"> <ul>
 <li><a href="#abstract">Abstract</a></li>
 <li><a href="#paper">Paper</a></li>
 <li><a href="#poster">Poster</a></li>
 <li><a href="#slides">Slides</a></li>
 <li><a href="#background">Background</a></li>
 </ul> </div>

  <div class="blog-main">
    <p>Shortlink: <a href="http://tiny.cc/hlcolt17" class="uri">http://tiny.cc/hlcolt17</a></p>
<h2 id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Deep neural nets have caused a revolution in many classification tasks. A related ongoing revolution–also theoretically not understood–concerns their ability to serve as generative models for complicated types of data such as images and texts. These models are trained using ideas like variational autoencoders and Generative Adversarial Networks.</p>
<p>We take a first cut at explaining the expressivity of multilayer nets by giving a sufficient criterion for a function to be approximable by a neural network with <span class="math inline"><em>n</em></span> hidden layers. A key ingredient is Barron’s Theorem [Barron1993], which gives a Fourier criterion for approximability of a function by a neural network with 1 hidden layer. We show that a composition of n functions which satisfy certain Fourier conditions (“Barron functions”) can be approximated by a <span class="math inline"><em>n</em> + 1</span>-layer neural network.</p>
<p>For probability distributions, this translates into a criterion for a probability distribution to be approximable in Wasserstein distance–a natural metric on probability distributions–by a neural network applied to a fixed base distribution (e.g., multivariate gaussian). Building up recent lower bound work, we also give an example function that shows that composition of Barron functions is more expressive than Barron functions alone.</p>
<h2 id="paper">Paper</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1702.07028">Arxiv page</a></li>
<li><a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1702.07028">PDF</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="poster">Poster</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/rjkc0u6estet9sz/barron_poster.pptx?dl=0">Powerpoint</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/4niwh4hkro6n882/barron_poster.pdf?dl=0">PDF</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="slides">Slides</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/lioa0e7wc8s8g3e/barron_presentation.pdf?dl=0">Slides</a></li>
<li><a href="https://workflowy.com/s/wL3CyEXpHY#/e7b2a09e6a24">Transcript</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="background">Background</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/4du02wdl58aaghk/barron1.pdf?dl=0">Expository note</a> on Barron’s Theorem.</p>
<p>Thoughts, questions, typos? Leave a comment below.</p>

  </div>

    

    <!-- Extension : Sharing buttons @ www.sharethis.com -->
    <span class='st_facebook_large' displayText='Facebook'></span>
    <span class='st_twitter_large' displayText='Tweet'></span>
    <span class='st_googleplus_large' displayText='Google +'></span>
    <span class='st_reddit_large' displayText='Reddit'></span>
    <span class='st__large' displayText=''></span>

    <div id="disqus_thread"></div>
    


  
    <script>!function(d,s,id){var js,fjs=d.getElementsByTagName(s)[0],p=/^http:/.test(d.location)?'http':'https';if(!d.getElementById(id)){js=d.createElement(s);js.id=id;js.src=p+'://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js';fjs.parentNode.insertBefore(js,fjs);}}(document, 'script', 'twitter-wjs');</script>
  </div>
  
</div>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Thoughts and links, 3-4/2017</title>
    <link href="http://holdenlee.github.io/blog/posts/monthly_summaries/2017-4.html" />
    <id>http://holdenlee.github.io/blog/posts/monthly_summaries/2017-4.html</id>
    <published>2017-05-01T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-05-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[
<div class="container">
  <div id="content">
    <div class="page header">
      <h1>Thoughts and links, 3-4/2017</h1>
    </div>
    
    <div class="info">
      
       
        <p>Posted: 2017-05-01 
          , Modified: 2017-05-01 
	</p>
      
       <p>Tags: <a href="/tags/links.html">links</a></p> 
    </div>
    
  </div>
  <!--/div-->

  

  <div class="blog-main">
    <p>See all the links for <a href="https://workflowy.com/s/wL3CyEXpHY#/d1a52d188a8f?q=%232017-3">March</a> and <a href="https://workflowy.com/s/wL3CyEXpHY#/d1a52d188a8f?q=%232017-4">April</a>. (See <a href="4-16.html">April 2016’s post</a> for an explanation of the organization.) Here are some highlights.</p>
<h2 id="books">Books</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/28202.The_Metaphysical_Club">The Metaphysical Club, Louis Menand</a>: Discusses the evolution of American philosophy in the 19th and early 20th century in response to the Civil War and scientific progress (ex. Darwin’s theory of evolution), through the story of 4 American philosphers (William James, Oliver Wendell Holmes, Charles Peirce, and John Dewey). <a href="https://workflowy.com/s/4qkO9xWz4M#/9ccd29dd9117">Notes</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/10165606-introduction-to-classical-chinese-philosophy">Introduction to classical Chinese philosophy, Bryan Van Norden</a>, <a href="https://workflowy.com/s/wL3CyEXpHY#/45fec88080b3">notes</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.rifters.com/real/Blindsight.htm">Blindsight, Peter Watts</a> asks the question: what if the correlation of consciousness and intelligence on Earth is just an accident - and the universe is filled with intelligent but nonconscious beings? It makes a strong (scientific, non-dualistic) argument for the possibility that intelligence need not be correlated with consciousness.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/3896708-china">China: A History, John Keay</a>: in progress, <a href="https://workflowy.com/s/wL3CyEXpHY#/0ad51ae14b7f">notes</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="comics">Comics</h2>
<p>A free trial of <a href="https://www.comixology.com/">Comixology</a> was very much worth it. Some of my picks:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.comixology.com/Trees-Vol-1/digital-comic/194144?ref=c2VhcmNoL2luZGV4L2Rlc2t0b3Avc2xpZGVyTGlzdC90b3BSZXN1bHRzU2xpZGVy">Trees</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.comixology.com/reMIND-Vol-1/digital-comic/197610?ref=c2VhcmNoL2luZGV4L2Rlc2t0b3Avc2xpZGVyTGlzdC90b3BSZXN1bHRzU2xpZGVy">reMIND</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.comixology.com/Adventure-Time-Vol-1/digital-comic/47066?ref=c2VhcmNoL2luZGV4L2Rlc2t0b3Avc2xpZGVyTGlzdC90b3BSZXN1bHRzU2xpZGVy">Adventure time</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.comixology.com/Adventure-Time-Fionna-Cake/comics-series/9458?ref=c2VhcmNoL2luZGV4L2Rlc2t0b3Avc2xpZGVyTGlzdC9zZXJpZXNTbGlkZXI">Fiona and Cake</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://www.comixology.com/Pretty-Deadly/comics-series/11683?ref=c2l0ZS9saXN0L2Rlc2t0b3AvbGlzdC9HZW5yZUxpc3Q">Pretty deadly</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="podcast-picks">Podcast Picks</h2>
<ul>
<li>The Allusionist
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.theallusionist.org/allusionist/please">33 Please</a>: Differences in the usage of “please” in the US and UK.</li>
<li>50-51 Under the Covers <a href="http://www.theallusionist.org/allusionist/covers-i">1</a> and <a href="http://www.theallusionist.org/allusionist/covers-ii">2</a>: On romance novels and the language of sex.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.theallusionist.org/allusionist/authority">54 The Authority</a>: The role of the dictionary.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="http://www.radiolab.org/story/radiolab-extra-henrietta-lacks/">Radiolab Extra: Henrietta Lacks</a>: On one woman’s medically miraculous cancer cells.</li>
<li>Imaginary Worlds: <a href="https://soundcloud.com/emolinsky/beyond-the-iron-curtain">Beyond the Iron Curtain</a>: Science fiction from the Soviet Union tends to be more subtle.</li>
<li>The Memory Palace: <a href="http://thememorypalace.us/2017/02/amok/">105, Amok</a>: when animals escape the Central Park Zoo.</li>
<li>On being: <a href="https://onbeing.org/https://onbeing.org/programs/richard-rohr-living-in-deep-time/">Richard Rohr — Living in Deep Time</a> (<a href="http://scrible.com/s/22FSA">highlights</a>): “Chronos is chronological time, time as duration, one moment after another, and that’s what most of us think of as time… But there was another word in Greek, kairos. And kairos was deep time. It was when you have those moments where you say, ‘Oh my god, this is it.’”</li>
<li>Philosophy Bites: <a href="http://philosophybites.com/2017/03/andy-clark-on-the-extended-mind.html">Andy Clark on The Extended Mind</a></li>
<li>Quanta: <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/20170202-math-and-the-best-life-francis-su-interview/">To live your best life, do mathematics</a>: Interview with Francis Su.</li>
<li>TED radio hour
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.npr.org/programs/ted-radio-hour/514152888/the-spirit-of-inquiry?showDate=2017-02-24">The spirit of inquiry</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.npr.org/programs/ted-radio-hour/519264798/decisions-decisions-decisions?showDate=2017-03-10">Decisions</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li>The Truth
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.thetruthpodcast.com/story/2017/3/8/miracle-on-the-l-train">Miracle on the L train</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li>This American Life:
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.thisamericanlife.org/radio-archives/episode/611/vague-and-confused">611 Vague and confused</a> including a story on who gets to stay on a private Hawaiian island.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.thisamericanlife.org/radio-archives/episode/614/the-other-mr-president">614 The other Mr. President</a> (Vladimir Putin)</li>
</ul></li>
<li>99 percent invisible
<ul>
<li><a href="http://99percentinvisible.org/episode/state-sanctuary-part-2/">250 State (Sanctuary Part 2)</a>: The role of churches as sanctuary in the refugee crisis.</li>
<li><a href="http://99percentinvisible.org/episode/containers-ships-tugs-port/">254 Containers</a>: The change brought by the invention of containers</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="articles">Articles</h2>
<ul>
<li>Map and territory:
<ul>
<li><a href="https://mapandterritory.org/need-dynamics-54ca9ff5955c">Need dynamics</a>: “Coference” seems like a useful concept.</li>
<li><a href="https://mapandterritory.org/narrativemancy-101-why-paper-beats-rock-bc25bc1147b6">Narrativemancy 101</a>: The power of narrative comes from how it references your most vivid feelings.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Slatestarcodex: <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2015/03/25/is-everything-a-religion/">Is everything a religion?</a></li>
<li><a href="http://lesswrong.com/lw/gej/i_attempted_the_ai_box_experiment_and_lost/">The AI box experiment</a></li>
<li><a href="https://blog.openai.com/evolution-strategies/">Evolutionary strategies</a> as an alternative to reinforcement learning (<a href="http://scrible.com/s/00V4A">h</a>)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="an-amazing-piece-of-my-little-pony-fanfiction">An amazing piece of My Little Pony Fanfiction</h2>
<p><a href="http://www.fimfiction.net/story/62074/friendship-is-optimal">Friendship is optimal</a></p>

  </div>

    

    <!-- Extension : Sharing buttons @ www.sharethis.com -->
    <span class='st_facebook_large' displayText='Facebook'></span>
    <span class='st_twitter_large' displayText='Tweet'></span>
    <span class='st_googleplus_large' displayText='Google +'></span>
    <span class='st_reddit_large' displayText='Reddit'></span>
    <span class='st__large' displayText=''></span>

    <div id="disqus_thread"></div>
    


  
    <script>!function(d,s,id){var js,fjs=d.getElementsByTagName(s)[0],p=/^http:/.test(d.location)?'http':'https';if(!d.getElementById(id)){js=d.createElement(s);js.id=id;js.src=p+'://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js';fjs.parentNode.insertBefore(js,fjs);}}(document, 'script', 'twitter-wjs');</script>
  </div>
  
</div>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Thoughts and links, 1-2/2017</title>
    <link href="http://holdenlee.github.io/blog/posts/monthly_summaries/2017-2.html" />
    <id>http://holdenlee.github.io/blog/posts/monthly_summaries/2017-2.html</id>
    <published>2017-03-05T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[
<div class="container">
  <div id="content">
    <div class="page header">
      <h1>Thoughts and links, 1-2/2017</h1>
    </div>
    
    <div class="info">
      
       
        <p>Posted: 2017-03-05 
          , Modified: 2017-03-05 
	</p>
      
       <p>Tags: <a href="/tags/links.html">links</a></p> 
    </div>
    
  </div>
  <!--/div-->

  

  <div class="blog-main">
    <p>See all the links for <a href="https://workflowy.com/s/wL3CyEXpHY#/d1a52d188a8f?q=%232017-1">January</a> and <a href="https://workflowy.com/s/wL3CyEXpHY#/d1a52d188a8f?q=%232017-2">February</a>. (See <a href="4-16.html">April’s post</a> for an explanation of the organization.) Here are some highlights.</p>
<h2 id="podcast-picks">Podcast picks</h2>
<ul>
<li>Imaginary worlds
<ul>
<li><a href="https://soundcloud.com/emolinsky/28-days-of-black-cosplay">28 days of black cosplay</a></li>
<li><a href="https://soundcloud.com/emolinsky/growing-up-avatar-american">Growing up Avatar-American</a>: Why is Avatar so popular among Asian-Americans?</li>
</ul></li>
<li>On being
<ul>
<li><a href="http://onbeing.org/programs/alain-de-botton-the-true-hard-work-of-love-and-relationships/">Alain de Botton - The true hard work of love and relationships</a> (<a href="https://workflowy.com/s/wL3CyEXpHY#/0d15c4e47c78">notes</a>)</li>
<li><a href="http://www.onbeing.org/programs/maria-popova-cartographer-meaning-digital-age/">Maria Popova - Cartographer of meaning in a digital age</a> (<a href="https://workflowy.com/s/wL3CyEXpHY#/e3859eac9b59">notes</a>)</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Radiolab
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.radiolab.org/story/stanger-paradise/">Stranger in paradise</a> Raccoons as an endangered species, or not?</li>
<li><a href="http://www.radiolab.org/story/radiolab-presents-media-busted-americas-poverty-myths/">On the media: busted, America’s poverty myths</a>.<a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"><sup>1</sup></a> See also <a href="http://freakonomics.com/podcast/american-dream-really-dead/">Freakonomics: Is the American Dream really dead?</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Rationally speaking
<ul>
<li><a href="http://rationallyspeakingpodcast.org/show/rs-176-jason-brennan-on-against-democracy.html">176 - Against Democracy</a> What if democracy is not the best system of government?</li>
<li><a href="http://static1.1.sqspcdn.com/static/f/468275/27460112/1487645326207/rs178transcript.pdf?token=awXHfsGHawhCx3qAlBjpX7HiISU%3D">178 - Tim Urban on “Trying to live well, as semi-rational animals”</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Reply All
<ul>
<li><a href="https://gimletmedia.com/episode/86-man-of-the-people/">86 Man of the people</a> A mindblowing story about how far a scammer got by harnessing the power of a new technology - the radio.</li>
<li><a href="https://gimletmedia.com/episode/87-longmont/">87 Storming the castle</a> Prank calls as an art form, by <a href="http://longmontpotioncastle.com/">Longmont potion castle</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Reveal (investigative reporting)
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.revealnews.org/episodes/the-year-in-reveal/">The year in Reveal</a>, including an interview with white nationalist Richard Spencer</li>
<li><a href="https://www.revealnews.org/episodes/the-man-inside-four-months-as-a-prison-guard/">The man inside: four months as a prison guard</a>: inside private prisons</li>
</ul></li>
<li>The Truth: <a href="http://www.thetruthpodcast.com/story/2017/1/11/the-dark-end-of-the-mall">The dark end of the mall</a> A post-apocalytic story</li>
<li>This American Life
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.thisamericanlife.org/radio-archives/episode/607/didn%E2%80%99t-we-solve-this-one">607 Didn’t we solve this one?</a> Iraqis risk their lives by helping American forces, but get rejected from immigration.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.thisamericanlife.org/radio-archives/episode/610/grand-gesture">610 Grand gestures</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li>99 percent invisible
<ul>
<li><a href="http://99percentinvisible.org/episode/the-revolutionary-post/">244 The revolutionary post</a> - history of the postal service</li>
<li>On Frank Lloyd Wright’s architecture: <a href="http://99percentinvisible.org/episode/usonia-1/">246 Usonia 1</a> and <a href="http://99percentinvisible.org/episode/usonia-the-beautiful/">247 Usonia the beautiful</a></li>
<li><a href="http://99percentinvisible.org/episode/atom-garden-eden/">248 Atom in the garden of Eden</a> - the dream of the nuclear age, manifested in “gamma gardens”</li>
</ul></li>
<li>青春愛消遣
<ul>
<li><a href="http://youngloveplay.blogspot.com/2017/02/056.html">56 愛上德國男</a>: A story about love and limerence.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="articles-and-websites">Articles and websites</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://zenpencils.com/">Zenpencils</a>: inspirational cartoon quotes</li>
<li>Rationality
<ul>
<li>Otium
<ul>
<li><a href="https://srconstantin.wordpress.com/2016/10/20/ra/">Ra</a> <a href="http://scrible.com/s/ifMm6">h</a>: A very good articulation of the corrupting force of generic superlativity. Related to Moloch, etc.</li>
<li><a href="https://srconstantin.wordpress.com/2016/03/21/there-is-no-secret-notebook/">There is no secret notebook</a> <a href="http://scrible.com/s/gDwm6">h</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Satvik Beri
<ul>
<li><a href="http://satvikberi.com/2016/12/26/increasing-output/">Increasing output</a>: Advice both for personal productivity and management.</li>
<li><a href="http://satvikberi.com/2015/03/31/efficiency-vs-disproportionate-results/">Efficiency vs. disproportionate results</a> <a href="http://scrible.com/s/kLx2C">h</a>: Two modes for solving problems that are too often disjoint.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cs.princeton.edu/news/crowd-wisdom-surprisingly-popular-answer-can-trump-ignorance-masses">“Surprisingly popular” answer can trump ignorance of the masses</a></li>
<li><a href="https://airtable.com/">Airtable</a>: Useful spreadsheet program which can save multiple sort/filter views</li>
<li>AI safety resources:
<ul>
<li><a href="http://humancompatible.ai/bibliography#corrigibility">Human-compatible AI bibliography</a></li>
<li><a href="https://agentfoundations.org/">Agent foundations</a> (the “forum digest” posts are very helpful)</li>
<li><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1606.06565">Concrete problems in AI safety</a></li>
<li><a href="https://intelligence.org/2016/07/27/alignment-machine-learning/">Alignment in machine learning</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="books">Books</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/332613.One_Flew_Over_the_Cuckoo_s_Nest">One flew over the cuckoo’s nest</a> - Set in a psychiatric hospital, but manages to a hopeful and humorous (and sad) story.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/7405989-the-dragon-and-the-stars">The dragon and the stars</a> - collection of Chinese-themed sci-fi/fantasy short stories</li>
<li>Farseer trilogy, Robin Hobb - follows the life of an assassin, with all its moral dilemmas. I liked the treatment of magic (the Skill - telepathic ability to talk with or influence other people - and the Wit - a communing with animals).
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/77197.Assassin_s_Apprentice">Assassin’s Apprentice, Robin Hobb</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25300956-royal-assassin">Royal Assassin, Robin Hobb</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18937.In_the_Beginning_Was_the_Command_Line">In the beginning was the command line, Neal Stephenson</a> - I wished I’d read this a long time ago; it illuminated some basic knowledge about computers which I lacked. A <a href="https://www.learnenough.com/command-line-tutorial">command line tutorial</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/22414.The_Invisible_Heart">The invisible heart: An economic romance, Russell Roberts</a> - A conversation about economics delightfully embedded in a love story. Made some good arguments for deregulation.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/156785.Diaspora">Diaspora, Greg Egan</a> - Greg Egan goes very far in imagining the evolution of minds in cyberspace. Some interesting metaphors for mathematics. Different ways of embedding life/computation in the universe. A journey through multiple universes in search for…?</li>
<li>Comics!
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25546167-descender-vol-1">Descender 1</a> After a mysterious AI wreaks destruction, robots are outlawed. Follows the story of an android who wakes up in this world.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/15704307-saga-vol-1">Saga 1</a> A couple from opposite sides of a galactic war tries to escape being hunted on all sides. Writing and art is fantastic. Also, +1 for Esperanto.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/22571552-so-you-ve-been-publicly-shamed">So you’ve been publicly shamed, Jon Ronson</a>. Starting with several stories of Twitter shaming gone out of control, investigates how public shaming has transformed in recent years, the morality and role of public shaming, how to mitigate it, etc.</li>
</ul>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>A quote: when we feel gratitude we’re more generous to strangers, when we’re more aware of luck’s importance, we’re more likely to plow our own fortune back into the common good. But we underplay luck because we can recall our own struggles far better than the fateful but fuzzy role of chance and because the very idea corrodes our faith in free will, but mostly because like Benny Franklin, we’re deeply invested in our own autobiographies.<a href="#fnref1">↩</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

  </div>

    

    <!-- Extension : Sharing buttons @ www.sharethis.com -->
    <span class='st_facebook_large' displayText='Facebook'></span>
    <span class='st_twitter_large' displayText='Tweet'></span>
    <span class='st_googleplus_large' displayText='Google +'></span>
    <span class='st_reddit_large' displayText='Reddit'></span>
    <span class='st__large' displayText=''></span>

    <div id="disqus_thread"></div>
    


  
    <script>!function(d,s,id){var js,fjs=d.getElementsByTagName(s)[0],p=/^http:/.test(d.location)?'http':'https';if(!d.getElementById(id)){js=d.createElement(s);js.id=id;js.src=p+'://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js';fjs.parentNode.insertBefore(js,fjs);}}(document, 'script', 'twitter-wjs');</script>
  </div>
  
</div>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Interactive Learning (Simons Workshop)</title>
    <link href="http://holdenlee.github.io/blog/posts/cs/ml/simons_ml_interactive.html" />
    <id>http://holdenlee.github.io/blog/posts/cs/ml/simons_ml_interactive.html</id>
    <published>2017-02-13T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[
<div class="container">
  <div id="content">
    <div class="page header">
      <h1>Interactive Learning (Simons Workshop)</h1>
    </div>
    
    <div class="info">
       <div class="subtitle"><p>Notes</p></div> 
       
        <p>Posted: 2017-02-13 
          , Modified: 2017-02-13 
	</p>
      
       <p>Tags: <a href="/tags/machine%20learning.html">machine learning</a></p> 
    </div>
    
  </div>
  <!--/div-->

  <div class="toc"></div>

  <div class="blog-main">
    <p>I’m currently attending the <a href="https://simons.berkeley.edu/workshops/machinelearning2017-1">Interactive Learning</a> workshop at the Simons Institute.</p>
<p>Here are my <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/mxbbdv8i11f63an/interactive_workshop.pdf?dl=0">notes</a>. Source is available on <a href="https://github.com/holdenlee/simons-ml">github</a>.</p>
<p>I’m also taking notes on seminars and reading groups at the Simons Program in Machine Learning. All notes are available on the <a href="http://simons.squidhive.net/Notes">Simons Program wiki</a>.</p>
<p>I will update this page as the workshop progresses.</p>

  </div>

    

    <!-- Extension : Sharing buttons @ www.sharethis.com -->
    <span class='st_facebook_large' displayText='Facebook'></span>
    <span class='st_twitter_large' displayText='Tweet'></span>
    <span class='st_googleplus_large' displayText='Google +'></span>
    <span class='st_reddit_large' displayText='Reddit'></span>
    <span class='st__large' displayText=''></span>

    <div id="disqus_thread"></div>
    


  
    <script>!function(d,s,id){var js,fjs=d.getElementsByTagName(s)[0],p=/^http:/.test(d.location)?'http':'https';if(!d.getElementById(id)){js=d.createElement(s);js.id=id;js.src=p+'://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js';fjs.parentNode.insertBefore(js,fjs);}}(document, 'script', 'twitter-wjs');</script>
  </div>
  
</div>
]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
